<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The first part of Protestants proofes, for Catholikes religion and recusancy Taken only from the vvritings, of such Protestant doctors and diuines of England, as haue beene published in the raigne of his Majesty ouer this kingdome.</title>
            <author>Broughton, Richard.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1607</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 121 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10168</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20448</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115460</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850679</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850679</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15902</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10168)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15902)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 933:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The first part of Protestants proofes, for Catholikes religion and recusancy Taken only from the vvritings, of such Protestant doctors and diuines of England, as haue beene published in the raigne of his Majesty ouer this kingdome.</title>
                  <author>Broughton, Richard.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 5-40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by the English secret press],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[England :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Domini. 1607.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Richard Broughton.</note>
                  <note>Identification of printer from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Of Protestant proofes, for Catholike religion.</note>
                  <note>E3v has the imprint of a French edition: A Paris. Chez François Gueffier, demeurant deuant la College de Cambray. M.D.C.VII.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Apologetic works --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Protestantism --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15902:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15902:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> THE FIRST PART OF PROTESTANTS PROOFES, FOR CATHO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIKES RELIGION AND RECVSANCY.</p>
            <p>Taken only from the vvritings, of ſuch <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Doctors and Diuines of <hi>England,</hi> as haue beene publiſhed in the raigne of his Majeſty ouer this Kingdome.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>PSAL. 1. verſ. 1.</bibl>
               <p>Bleſſed is the man that hath not gone in the counſaile of the vngodly.</p>
            </q>
            <p>ANNO DOMINI. 1607.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:15902:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:15902:2"/>
            <head>TO THE MOST HONOV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RABLE LORDES. AND OTHERS, OF HIS MA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>IESTIES PRIVIE COVN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CELL.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>OST HONOVRABLE.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>As nothing can be leſſe concea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, then the long, manifold, and knowne miſeries of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Catholikes,</hi> for their ancient faith: So if we conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, by what plots and practizes, the aduancement of <hi>Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biterall</hi> diſcipline, hath beene and daylie is more and more affected, and only or chiefly (as the defendors thereof pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe<note n="a" place="margin">Iacob p. 73. of his reaſons. Proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in the end of the confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence 1603. Purit. offer of confer. &amp;c.</note>) receiuing obſtacle in courſe of learning, by the groundes of <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like</hi> religion: The pennes and pulpits of <hi>Puritans,</hi> and their Printers will ſufficiently write, preach and publiſh to the world, by whome and to what purpoſe, no ſmal part of theſe afflictions haue beene vrged and incited againſt vs; not only by thoſe fewe, which refuſe your externall conformity, but ſuch as (for a faſhion) followe it, to retayne themſelues in authority.</p>
            <p>For proofe whereof, the greateſt number of the preſent <hi>Proteſtant</hi> wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, <hi>D. Sutcliffe</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Sutcliffe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt D. Kel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſon, pag. 42.</note>, D. Doue<note n="c" place="margin">Doue per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion, p. 31.</note>, <hi>D. Field</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Field p. 170.</note>, M. Willet<note n="e" place="margin">Willet An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilog. pa. 275.</note>, <hi>Wotton</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Wotton de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of Perkins, pag. 28.</note>, Middleton<note n="g" place="margin">Middleton papiſtomaſtix, p. 201.</note>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> doe teach, <hi>there is no matter of faith, no ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall, eſſentiall, or materiall point or difference in religion,</hi> betweene <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> and <hi>Puritans:</hi> But they are of one <hi>Church, Faith, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</hi> Then either they be <hi>Puritans,</hi> or of no religion: and it is not mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall with them, whether men be of a true, or falſe religion, of any, or none at all. For his Majeſty<note n="h" place="margin">K. ſpeach in Parl. 1603<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> conference at Hampton, p. 36. 80. 81. 82.</note>, the Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">B. of Wincheſt. Suruey, pag. 466. 467. 474. 486. &amp;c.</note>, <hi>D. Couell</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Couell defence of Hooker, p. 68. againſt Burges in Prefat. &amp; pag. 33.</note> (two of your beſt writers) <hi>M. Parkes</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Parkes againſt lymbomaſtix, pag. 92. 93. &amp; Prefat. &amp; Apolog. Epiſtol. dedicat.</note>, <hi>M. Ormerod</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Ormerod Epist. dedicat. pict. Purit. &amp;c.</note>, and others; conclude from their doctrine, and their owne bookes extant tell vs: Their religion is to
<pb facs="tcp:15902:3"/> beleeue; <hi>that euery Prince, King, or Emperor diſanulling the</hi> Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitery <hi>is enemy to God, vnworthy to raigne, to be reſiſted by force of armes, not to be prayed for: No King, no Monarchy, no Biſhop, no true Church in</hi> England, <hi>or whereſoeuer their</hi> Preſbitery <hi>wanteth.</hi> The article of Chriſtes diſcent to hell, <hi>is an jdle and vaine fanſie, a meere dreame an intruded fable, a pernitious hereſie. Chriſt was a ſinner, ſuffered the torments of the damned, his diuinity, humanity, and ſaluation, heauen and hell, are queſtioned: the foundation it ſelfe is ſhaken.</hi> And ſuch Profeſſors haue profeſſed, and profited ſo farre, that by outward ſignes, communion, profeſsion, proteſtation, ſubſcription, no man can tell, who is of what religion among them. For men by this doctrine (as his Highnes<note n="n" place="margin">Conference, ſupr. pag. 82.</note> hath noted) will denie their religion, <hi>to make their party good againſt the Biſhops.</hi> A chiefe Profeſſor, may profeſſe<note n="o" place="margin">Willet Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>log. in prefat. Latin.</note> to our So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne, <hi>Puritanus non ſum: I am no Puritan,</hi> to haue better meanes to write<note n="p" place="margin">Willet lym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bomaſtix.</note> 
               <hi>Lymbomaſtix,</hi> and<note n="q" place="margin">Parkes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt lymbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſtix p. 106</note> 
               <hi>become the greateſt promoter of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended diſcipline.</hi> Though a Miniſter <hi>ſubſcribe-foure times,</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Burges Apol &amp; apud Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell againſt Burges.</note> He may <hi>defend both that and refuſall; lawfull,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, ſeing ſuch teachers by ſuch meanes (as <hi>Proteſtants</hi> acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge)<note n="ſ" place="margin">Parkes Apol. epiſt. dedicat. Couel againſt Barg. in pref.</note> 
               <hi>Make way for Atheiſme and Infidelity;</hi> and<note n="t" place="margin">Parkes ſupr. epiſt. dedicat.</note> 
               <hi>men ſay, they knowe whome to flie, but whome to followe they cannot tell:</hi> I hope it unto heynous ſinne in <hi>Catholikes,</hi> not to followe ſuch conductors. And for further excuſe, becauſe they write they<note n="u" place="margin">Vniuerſity of Oxfor. againſt the Millinar. petition, p. 32</note> are <hi>more famous for learning, then all the Miniſters of Europe;</hi> and yet, doe not only refuſe all equall triall offered by vs, but either cal<note n="x" place="margin">Willet Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. triumph. pag. 40. &amp; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pud Parkes againſt lym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bomaſt. p. 28.</note> the rules and principles of religion, which his Majeſty approueth (and we humbly accept) <hi>a fooliſh conceit and ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination,</hi> or<note n="y" place="margin">Wotton de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins, p. 15. 16</note> vtterly reject them, and will only be tryed by themſelues: A poore <hi>Catholike</hi> Student, in moſt dutifull manner preſenteth vnto your Honours, theſe <hi>Proteſtant</hi> proofes, for all chiefe points of <hi>Catholike</hi> reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, only taken from their owne writings, ſince the beginning of his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties raigne in <hi>England.</hi> Firſt (to giue them all aduantage) becauſe in this time, they haue written ſo much and ſo vncharitably againſt vs, that one of their owne number,<note n="z" place="margin">Omer. pict. pap. in poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript. epiſt.</note> adjudgeth many of their bookes to the fire, and their au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thours worthy death. Secondly, becauſe I cannot tell, whether they wil allow what they wrote, or taught in the dayes of Queene <hi>Elizabeth;</hi> ſeing they defend, they may often change, &amp; doe (<note n="*" place="margin">Doue per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, p. 31.</note> 
               <hi>at the leaſt) at the change of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery Prince.</hi> And ſo with all ſubmiſsiue respect, I leaue this cauſe to your wiſeſt conſideration, and your most Honourable perſons to Gods protection.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:15902:3"/>
            <head>THE FIRST PART OF PROTESTANTS PROOFES, FOR CATHOLIKES RELIGION AND RECVSANCY.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Chapter the firſt.</hi> Of the ſupreame and moſt preeminent authority of the true Church: howe neceſſary it is to finde it, followe the directions, and rest in the judgement of it.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>OCTOR FIELD a late <hi>Proteſtant</hi> writer, beginneth his dedicatory Epiſtle to the L. Archbiſhoppe of <hi>Canterbury</hi> (before his bookes of the Church) in this ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner.<note n="a" place="margin">D. Field of the Church epiſt. dedicat.</note> 
                  <hi>There is no part of heauenly doctrine more neceſſary, in theſe daies of ſo many intricate controuerſies of religion, then diligently to ſearch out, which among al the ſocieties of men in the world, is that bleſſed company of holy-ones, that houſe-hold of faith, that ſpouſe of Chriſt, and Church of the liuing God, which is the piller and ground of truth: that ſo they may em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace her communion, followe her directions, and reſt in her judgement.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>D. Couel</hi> writeth of the Church in theſe wordes:<note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Couell de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of Hoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, pag.</hi> 30. <hi>art.</hi> 4.</note> 
                  <hi>That which by her</hi> Eccleſiaſticall <hi>authority, ſhee ſhall probably thinke, and define to be true, or good; muſt in congruity of reaſon, ouer-rule all other inferior judgements whatſoeuer. And to them that (out of a ſingularity of their owne) aſke vs why we thus bang our judgements on the Churcbes ſleeue? we anſwere with</hi> Salomon, <hi>two are better then one. For euen in matters of leſſe moment, it</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 4. <hi>v.</hi> 9</note> 
                  <hi>was neuer thought ſafe, to neglect the judgement of many, &amp; raſhly to follow the fancy and opinion of ſome fewe.</hi> And in another place thus he citeth <hi>D. Whitakers</hi> to the ſame purpoſe:<note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>Couell cont. Burges p.</hi> 60.</note> 
                  <hi>The Church of Chriſt according to her authority receiued from him, hath warrant to approue the Scriptures, to acknowledge, to receiue, to publiſh and command vnto her children.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>M. Wotton</hi> witneſſeth:<note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>Wotton de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins, pa.</hi> 442.</note> 
                  <hi>The judgement of the Church we are ſo farre from diſcrediting, that we hold it for a very ſpeciall ground in this matter of Scriptures.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>M. Ormerods</hi> wordes be theſe:<note n="e" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ormerod pict pap. pag.</hi> 93.</note> 
                  <hi>The Church is called a piller, becauſe it is like vnto a piller. For as a piller doth ſupporte and vnder-proppe a buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, &amp; maketh it more ſtable, firme and ſtrong: ſo the Church doth ſuſtaine, and ſupport the truth; for the truth is no where preſerued but in the Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>D. Sutcliffe</hi> approueth this ſentence:<note n="f" place="margin">
                     <hi>Sutcliffe againſt th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> three co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſ. pag.</hi> 7<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Chriſtes true Church is a dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent</hi>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:15902:4"/> 
                  <hi>and wary keeper of doctrines committed to her, and changeth nothing at any time, diminiſheth nothing, addeth nothing ſuperfluous, looſeth not her owne, nor vſurpeth thinges belonging to others.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Neither is this different from their publike doctrine, thus decreed in the twenty Article of their religion:<note n="g" place="margin">
                     <hi>Articul.</hi> 20. 1562.</note> 
                  <hi>The Church hath power to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree Rites or Ceremonies, and authority in controuerſies of faith.</hi> And the joyning with this true Church of Chriſt is ſo needfull a thing, that <hi>D. Field</hi> concludeth:<note n="h" place="margin">
                     <hi>Field, p.</hi> 69.</note> 
                  <hi>There is no ſaluation, remiſsion of ſinnes, or hope of eternall life out of the Church.</hi> Like is the judgement of <hi>D. Couell</hi>
                  <note n="i" place="margin">
                     <hi>Couell def. of Hooker. pag.</hi> 76.</note> and others. Wherefore, ſeing <hi>Catholikes</hi> profeſſe themſelues members of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church; before they thinke of forſaking it, let vs ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine, vvhether theſe <hi>Proteſtants</hi> vvill not allowe it for this true Church of Chriſt, ſo dignified by their doctrine.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Chapter 2.</hi> The <hi>Roman</hi> Church euer was, and ſtill is by theſe <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> the tru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Church of Chriſt: it continueth all thinges belonging to ſaluation: they which liue and die therein, may be ſaued.</head>
               <p>THE <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Relator of religion vvriteth thus, of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church:<note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Relation of the ſtate of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, ca.</hi> 48.</note> 
                  <hi>There are amongſt them (vndoubtedly) in great multitude, men vertuous, learned, fraught with the loue of God, and the truth aboue all thinges, men of memorable integrity, of bart &amp; affections.</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Cap.</hi> 6.</note> 
                  <hi>In their ſermons much matter both of faith and piety, is eloquently deliuered, by men of won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull zeale, and ſpirit.</hi>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>Cap.</hi> 6. <hi>ſupr.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>The outward ſtate and glory of their ſeruice, doth ingender, quicken, encreaſe, and nouriſh the inward reuerence, respect, and deuotion, which is due vnto ſoueraigne Majeſty, and power.</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>Cap.</hi> 9.</note> 
                  <hi>Their deedes of charity are exceeding.</hi>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">
                     <hi>Cap.</hi> 22. 26.</note> 
                  <hi>No ſeuerity of life comparable to ſome of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious.</hi> If <hi>Proteſtants</hi> were, or would be at vnion with them;<note n="f" place="margin">
                     <hi>Cap.</hi> 48.</note> 
                  <hi>they ſhall find excellent order of gouernement, ſinguler helpes for encreaſe of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines &amp; deuotion, for the conquering of ſinne, for the profiting of vertue.</hi> And perſwading an vnion, he only requireth <hi>Catholikes</hi> to giue ouer fiue thinges, al diſpenſable, and not any of them eſſential, as he teacheth: And aduiſeth <hi>Proteſtants</hi> to change their religion vnto vs, with that condition. Secondly, we are aſſured, that the higheſt authority of Chriſts Church is in the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, or in none at all: for <hi>D. Field</hi> writeth:<note n="g" place="margin">
                     <hi>Field p.</hi> 228</note> 
                  <hi>That the ſupreame binding and commanding authority, is only in Biſhops in a generall Councell:</hi> ſo <hi>D. Morton</hi>
                  <note n="h" place="margin">
                     <hi>Morto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> part.</hi> 2. <hi>Apol. p.</hi> 340</note>, <hi>D. Sutcliffe</hi>
                  <note n="i" place="margin">
                     <hi>Sutc. againſt D. Kelliſon, p.</hi> 41. 42. 102</note>, the Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter</hi>
                  <note n="k" place="margin">
                     <hi>B. Bilſons Suruey, p.</hi> 85.</note>, and others. But all men knowe and <hi>D. Sutcliffe,</hi> with
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:15902:4"/> others acknowledge, the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> haue had no ſuch Councell; ſo the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Relator of religion teacheth,<note n="e" place="margin">
                     <hi>Relation of relig. cap.</hi> 47.</note> that this preeminence, meanes, and remedy is only in the <hi>Roman</hi> Church.</p>
               <p>Secondly, to make tryall by their publike definition of the Church: The <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Articles teach;<note n="f" place="margin">
                     <hi>Articul.</hi> 19.</note> 
                  <hi>The viſible Church of Chriſt, is a congregation of faithfull men, in the which the pure worde of God is preached, and the Sacraments be duly miniſtred, according to Chriſtes ordinance, in all thoſe thinges that of neceſsity are requiſite to the ſame. D. Couell</hi>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">
                     <hi>Couell de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of Hoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, pag.</hi> 67.</note>, <hi>D. Field</hi>
                  <note n="h" place="margin">
                     <hi>Field, p.</hi> 25.</note>, and <hi>D. Doue</hi>
                  <note n="i" place="margin">
                     <hi>D. Doue per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſ. pag.</hi> 23.</note>, be of the ſame minde. But becauſe the <hi>Puritans</hi> adde a third note, I will cite <hi>D. Couell</hi> in this queſtion: his wordes be theſe.<note n="k" place="margin">
                     <hi>Couell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the plea of the Innoc. pag.</hi> 21. 56.</note> 
                  <hi>There be but two eſſentiall notes of the Church, the true preaching of the word, and the right adminiſtration of the Sacraments;</hi> to which later <hi>Proteſtants</hi> adde <hi>diſcipline the third note, and of as much neceſsity.</hi> And concerning doctrine and Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments they generally teach, that they are truly taught and practiſed in the Church, <hi>only in eſſentiall, neceſſary, requiſite, and fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall thinges;</hi> ſo the<note n="l" place="margin">
                     <hi>Articul.</hi> 19.</note> ninetenth Article before; ſo <hi>M. Willet</hi> in theſe wordes.<note n="m" place="margin">
                     <hi>Willet An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilog. pag.</hi> 43.</note> 
                  <hi>To errours of doctrine which are not fundamentall, euen the true Church of Christ is ſubject:</hi> ſo <hi>D. Field</hi>
                  <note n="n" place="margin">D. Field of the Church</note> ordinarily in his bookes of the Church: ſo <hi>D. Sutcliffe</hi>
                  <note n="o" place="margin">
                     <hi>Sutc. againſt D. Kelliſ. p.</hi> 42</note>, <hi>D. Doue</hi>
                  <note n="p" place="margin">
                     <hi>Doue perſw. pag.</hi> 31. 32.</note>, <hi>M. Wotton</hi>
                  <note n="q" place="margin">
                     <hi>Wotto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, p.</hi> 28</note>, <hi>M. Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleton</hi>
                  <note n="r" place="margin">
                     <hi>Middleton. pag.</hi> 201.</note>, <hi>Powell</hi>
                  <note n="ſ" place="margin">Powel conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, &amp;c.</note>, and all the reſt making <hi>Proteſtants</hi> and <hi>Puritans</hi> but one Church, doe and muſt acknowledge.</p>
               <p>Then concerning doctrine, <hi>D. Doue</hi> writeth in theſe tearmes:<note n="t" place="margin">
                     <hi>Doue perſw. pag.</hi> 11.</note> 
                  <hi>In fundamentall points of doctrine the greateſt</hi> Papiſts <hi>in the world agree with vs.</hi> And in his vvhole Treatiſe neuer chargeth the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> either of <hi>Schiſme</hi> or <hi>Hereſie,</hi> but laboureth to excuſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, offering that we ſhall communicate with them, without any change of opinion: and yet he ſetteth downe this for an infallible propoſition.<note n="u" place="margin">
                     <hi>page</hi> 5.</note> 
                  <hi>This propoſition is vndoubtedly true; no</hi> Heretikes <hi>nor</hi> Schiſmatikes <hi>are to be communicated withall.</hi> And he giueth vs ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity, that by no poſſibility (according to the former reaſon of generall Councels) the <hi>Roman</hi> Church can be judged <hi>Hereticall;</hi> his vvordes be theſe:<note n="x" place="margin">
                     <hi>page</hi> 14.</note> 
                  <hi>No Church can be condemned and adjudged</hi> He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticall <hi>by any priuate cenſure, but it must be publike; A generall Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell,</hi> as he there expoundeth himſelfe, and is graunted before. Touching Sacraments, he alloweth,<note n="y" place="margin">
                     <hi>pag.</hi> 27. 28<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> that according to our defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Sacrament, <hi>There be as many as we teach, and this ſhall not breede any ſuch jarre betweene vs, that therefore we ſhould refuſe to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate</hi>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:15902:5"/> 
                  <hi>together.</hi> And tranſubſtantiation it ſelfe ſhall be <hi>no barre,</hi>
                  <note n="z" place="margin">
                     <hi>page</hi> 29.</note> But if we vvill receiue <hi>at their handes, they will not examine howe we</hi> doe expound the vvordes, <hi>hoc eſt corpus meum.</hi> And of diſcipline the third note, he noteth: <hi>In that Councell of</hi> Trent, <hi>they ſet forth ſuch holeſome Canons concerning diſcipline, as were fit for a reformed Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Relator of religion affirmeth:<note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Relation of relig. cap.</hi> 48</note> 
                  <hi>That the</hi> Roman <hi>Church ſtill keepeth inuiolable, the foundation of religion.</hi> And I thinke no man vvill denie the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> to be the ſame it vvas at the comming of <hi>Luther,</hi> and long before; and yet <hi>D. Field</hi> vvriteth:<note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Field, p.</hi> 72.</note> 
                  <hi>The</hi> Roman <hi>and</hi> Latin <hi>Church continued the true Church of God, euen till our time.</hi> And againe:<note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>page</hi> 182.</note> 
                  <hi>We doubt not but the Church in which the Biſhop of</hi> Rome <hi>exalted himſelfe</hi> (he addeth, <hi>with more then</hi> Lucifer-like <hi>pride) was notwithſtanding the true Church of God: that it held a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing profeſsion of the truth in Chriſt, and by force thereof, conuerted many countries from errour to the way of truth.</hi> And he further acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth<note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>page</hi> 72.</note> with <hi>D. Couell</hi> and others:<note n="e" place="margin">
                     <hi>Couel defen. of Hook. p.</hi> 73</note> 
                  <hi>That</hi> Luther <hi>and the reſt of his religion, were baptiſed, receiued their Chriſtianity, ordination, and power of Miniſtery, in that Church, as the true, viſible, and apparant Church of Chriſt.</hi> He telleth vs further,<note n="f" place="margin">
                     <hi>Field p.</hi> 182.</note> That diuers of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Church not only of the ignorant, but of the beſt learned be ſaued, and Saints in heauen. <hi>M. Willets</hi> vvordes be theſe:<note n="g" place="margin">
                     <hi>Willet An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilog. pa.</hi> 144.</note> 
                  <hi>It is not denyed by any</hi> Proteſtant, <hi>but many renowmed Kings and Queenes (which might not pleade ignorance, of the</hi> Roman <hi>faith) are Saints in heauen.</hi> And ſpeaking of his Majeſties Mother, hee attributeth ſuch holyneſſe and truth to her religion, and her; that it preuailed vvith God, not only for her ſelfe, but her Sonne our Soueraigne alſo, his vvordes be:<note n="h" place="margin">Willet An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilog. Engl. pref to the K.</note> 
                  <hi>The child of ſuch prayers and teares, cannot poſsibly fall away.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Who are accompted the greateſt Schollers, but the ſchoole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men chiefe in ſchooles? And yet, both <hi>D. Sutcliffe</hi> tearmeth theſe (<note n="i" place="margin">
                     <hi>Sutcl. anſw. to the lay pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition, pa.</hi> 34.</note> namely, <hi>Innocent</hi> the third, <hi>Thomas Aquihas, Scotus, Albert, Durand)</hi> particuler agents of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, and joyneth them in that ſence, vvith <hi>Harding, Allen, Bellarmine, Baronius.</hi> And <hi>D. Couell</hi> ſpeaking of the high praiſes of ſuch men, writeth of <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander Hales, S. Bonauenture,</hi> and <hi>S. Thomas</hi> before recited for the Popes agent in theſe vvordes.<note n="k" place="margin">
                     <hi>Couell def. of Hooker, pag.</hi> 241.</note> Alexander Hales, <hi>who made his ſumme that excellent worke, by commandement of Pope</hi> Innocentius <hi>the</hi>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:15902:5"/> 
                  <hi>fourth, was called the fountayne of life, becauſe of that liuely knowledge, that flowed from him: he was Master to</hi> Bonauenture, <hi>a Scholler not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior to himſelfe, of whome he was wont to ſay, that in</hi> Bonauenture <hi>he thought</hi> Adam <hi>ſinned not; meaning of that illumination which was in him (and doubtleſſe there was much in him) as though he had not beene darkened by the fall of</hi> Adam: <hi>and therefore the Church called him the Seraphicall Doctor. To theſe</hi> Aquinas <hi>was not inferior, who came ſo neare vnto</hi> S. Auguſtine, (vvhome in his booke againſt <hi>Burges</hi> he eſteemeth<note n="l" place="margin">Co. againſt Burges.</note> the chiefeſt Doctor that euer was, or ſhall be, excepting the Apoſtles, <hi>&amp;c.) that ſome thought he had all his workes by hart, and by a common prouerbe it was ſpoken, that the ſoule of</hi> S. Auguſtine <hi>dwelt in</hi> Aquinas: <hi>in whome aboue all the reſt, foure contrarieties were ſaid to excell; aboundance, breuity, facility, ſecurity: in respect whereof, he gay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the title to be called Angelicall.</hi> Then if theſe men were the Popes agents; and yet ſo renowmed and glorious, and their doctrine ſo ſecure and excellent, vve may ſecurely followe them, in the ſame ſteps of agency of ſuch buſineſſe.</p>
               <p>And to paſſe Princes, Doctors, and Popes agents, and come to the Popes themſelues. The <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Relator of religion<note n="m" place="margin">
                     <hi>Relation of religion, cap.</hi> 43. 42.</note> hath found much vertue, deuotion, and piety, of thoſe vvhich haue beene in theſe times; and of the laſt Pope <hi>Clement</hi> the eight, he wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth thus: <hi>He did often weepe vpon piety and Godly compaſsion, at his Maſſes, Proceſsions,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>His eyes were ſtill watering, ſome-times ſtrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming with teares, in ſo much that for weeping be ſeemed an other</hi> Heracli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus: <hi>he was a good Pope, a good Man, a good Prince, a good Prelate.</hi> And to exclude ignorance, the ſame Relator witneſſeth thus:<note n="n" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ca.</hi> 29. <hi>ſupr.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>The</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts <hi>cry mainely in all places for triall by disputation.</hi> D. <hi>Couell</hi> againe vvitneſſeth thus of <hi>Catholikes:</hi>
                  <note n="o" place="margin">
                     <hi>Couel def. of Hook. pa.</hi> 68.</note> 
                  <hi>Touching the maine points of Chriſtian truth, they conſtantly perſiſt in them.</hi> Proteſtants <hi>doe gladly acknowledge them to be the family of</hi> Ieſus <hi>Christ.</hi> And againe;<note n="p" place="margin">
                     <hi>pa.</hi> 68. <hi>ſupr.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>They of</hi> Rome <hi>were, and are ſtill in the Church, a part of the houſe of God, a limme of the viſible Church:</hi> which he addeth alſo to haue beene <hi>M. Hookers</hi>
                  <note n="q" place="margin">
                     <hi>Hooker l.</hi> 5. <hi>pag.</hi> 188.</note> ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, telling vs, that vvhat he vvriteth of the Church of <hi>Rome, is but to giue her, her due; and we acknowledge them to be of the family of</hi> Ieſus <hi>Christ.</hi> And concludeth thus:<note n="r" place="margin">
                     <hi>Couell ſupr. pag.</hi> 73.</note> 
                  <hi>It is ſtrange for any man to denie them of</hi> Rome <hi>to be of the Church.</hi> And againe:<note n="ſ" place="margin">
                     <hi>page</hi> 76.</note> 
                  <hi>We affirme them of the</hi> Roman <hi>Church, to be parts of the Church of Christ, and that thoſe that liue and die in that Church, may be ſaued.</hi> And all kindes of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:15902:6"/> 
                  <hi>Proteſtants</hi> when they combate among themſelues, rather preferre the <hi>Roman</hi> Church to be choſen and followed, then their oppoſite <hi>Proteſtants.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Relator witneſſeth:<note n="t" place="margin">
                     <hi>Relation of relig. cap.</hi> 45.</note> 
                  <hi>The</hi> Lutherans <hi>in</hi> Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, <hi>both the Clergie and Laytie openly proteſt, they will rather returne to the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>then joyne with the Sacramentary</hi> Proteſtants; <hi>ſuch as be in England.</hi> The <hi>Puritans</hi> of this nation<note n="u" place="margin">Offer of conference.</note> in their late of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer of Conference, preferre the <hi>Roman</hi> Church farre before their country <hi>Proteſtants.</hi> Of the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> there vvill be as little que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, by this Treatiſe: And in particuler <hi>M. Iacob</hi> writeth thus:<note n="x" place="margin">
                     <hi>Iacob, p.</hi> 73.</note> 
                  <hi>The Biſhops of</hi> England <hi>when they deale with</hi> Puritans, <hi>muſt joyne plainely with the</hi> Catholikes <hi>in their anſwers, if they will maintayne themſelues.</hi> So much and more is teſtified in two ſeuerall <hi>Proteſtant</hi> letters,<note n="y" place="margin">
                     <hi>The firſt co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Iannar.</hi> 15 1603. <hi>the</hi> 2. <hi>copy in the end of the conference.</hi>
                  </note> printed in the end of <hi>D. Barlowes</hi> booke, of the confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence at <hi>Hampton:</hi> which for reſpect, I paſſe ouer without particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler citation.</p>
               <p>Wherefore, by all agreement both of <hi>Catholikes</hi> affirming this and more, and <hi>Proteſtants</hi> acknowledging this; <hi>The</hi> Roman <hi>Church is ſtill the true Church of Chriſt, it contayneth and continueth all thinges ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to ſaluation, they which liue and die therein may be ſaued;</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the true Church, by the<note n="z" place="margin">
                     <hi>Articul.</hi> 19. 1562. <hi>Couell defen. of Hoo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ker, pag.</hi> 67.</note> ninetenth Article of <hi>Proteſtant</hi> reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, it muſt needes be (as before is cited) <hi>a congregation of faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full men, in the which the pure word of God is preached, and the Sacraments be duly miniſtred, according to Chriſtes ordinance, in all thoſe thinges that of neceſsity are requiſite to the ſame.</hi> Then ſeing according to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties ſentence:<note n="a" place="margin">King-ſpeach in Parliam.</note> 
                  <hi>I acknowledge the</hi> Roman <hi>Church to be our mother Church.</hi> And in the publike conference, his regall reſolution be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this:<note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Conference at Hampton, pag.</hi> 75.</note> 
                  <hi>That no Church ought further to ſeperate it ſelfe from the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>either in doctrine or ceremony, then ſhee hath departed from her ſelfe, when ſhee was in her flouriſhing and beſt eſtate,</hi> and from <hi>Chriſt her Lord and head;</hi> vvhich by the teſtimonies before is nothing at al in any neceſſary queſtion; but ſtil it joyneth vs to Chriſt, both by doctrine and Sacraments in this life, and with glory in heauen: therefore, we may not forſake it in earth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:15902:6"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Chapter 3.</hi> Wherein theſe <hi>Proteſtants</hi> teach, the neceſsity of one ſupreame ſpirituall head, and commander in the Church of Chriſt: howe <hi>S. Peter</hi> was this chiefe among the Apoſtles: and after him, his ſucceſſors the Popes of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IF vve examine a little further, the teſtimonies of theſe men: whereas ſome vnchriſtian ſermons and bookes, haue heretofore tearmed the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> to be the great Antichriſt, and ſeducer of the vvorld; vve ſhall nowe receiue a better doctrine, and more religious anſwere: That there euer was and muſt be, one chiefe and ſupreame ſpirituall head, and commander of the Church of Chriſt in earth: That in the time of the Apoſtles and among them, it vvas <hi>S. Peter</hi> the firſt Biſhop of <hi>Rome:</hi> And after him, the Biſhops and Popes of that ſame Apoſtolike See, therein ſucceeding in that ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preame binding and commanding authority. <hi>D. Field</hi> citeth and approueth this,<note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Field. pag.</hi> 138.</note> as a generall and infallible rule: <hi>Eccleſiae ſalus in ſummi Sacerdotis dignitate pendet,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>The health of the Church de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendeth on the dignity of the high Prieſt, whoſe eminent authority if it be denyed, then will be ſo many</hi> Schiſmes <hi>in the Church as there be Prieſts:</hi> then of neceſſity one chief, ſupreame, &amp; high Prieſt, muſt be aſſigned in his judgement. And <hi>D. Couell</hi> entreating of this ſpirituall, and higheſt Monarchicall regiment, and neceſſity thereof, writeth thus:<note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Couell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the plea of the Innocent. pag.</hi> 106.</note> 
                  <hi>We eaſily ſee that equality doth breede factions, and therefore wiſemen to ſuppreſſe the ſeedes of diſſentions, haue made one aboue the reſt.</hi> And that no man ſhould eſteeme this as an humane ordinance, either prouided by Councels, as ſome <hi>Proteſtants</hi> vvould perſwade; or giuen or graunted by <hi>Phocas</hi> the Emperor, about the yeare of our Lord 607. <hi>for</hi> Boniface <hi>then Pope &amp; his ſucceſſors</hi> (to vſe <hi>D. Downames</hi> wordes<note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>Downame lib.</hi> 1. <hi>pag.</hi> 4.</note>) <hi>to be head of the</hi> Catholike <hi>or vniuerſall Church:</hi> This <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant</hi> authour both teſtifieth, and proueth it to be the inſtitution of Chriſt himſelfe; and firſt among his Apoſtles, of whome he ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth thus:<note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>Couell ſupr. pag.</hi> 106.</note> 
                  <hi>Becauſe in the execution of holy thinges, where the perſons put in truſt are but men, diſcord and diſorder vſually doe breake in; the wiſdome of God thought it neceſſary, that amongſt them, who for their miniſtery were equall, an inequality for order, and ſuperiority to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, ſhould be graunted: that by this meanes, order and vnion ſhould both be preſerued in Chriſtes Church. Which, if it concerne all perſons</hi>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:15902:7"/> 
                  <hi>and ages in the Church of Chriſt, (as ſurely it doth) the gouernement muſt not ceaſe with the Apoſtles.</hi> And againe, hee proueth this ſpirituall ſupreamacy to bee perpetuall, becauſe novve there is more neede in theſe times of ſinne and diſſentions; And yet (ſaith he):<note n="e" place="margin">
                     <hi>Couell ſupr. pag.</hi> 107.</note> 
                  <hi>It was the principall meanes to preuent Schiſmes and diſſentions in the primatiue Church, when the graces of God were farre more aboundant and eminent, then nowe they are: nay, if the twelue were not like to agree, except there had beene one chiefe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them: for ſaith</hi> Saint Hierome, <hi>amongſt the twelue one was therefore choſen, that a chiefe being appointed, occaſion of diſſention might be preuented,</hi> &amp;c. And he diſputeth thus againſt the <hi>Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritans:</hi>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">
                     <hi>Supr. pag.</hi> 107.</note> 
                  <hi>Howe can they thinke that equality would keepe all the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors of the world in vnity?</hi> And adjudgeth this ſupreame ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall power ſo neceſſary in the Church of God, that he addeth: <hi>Seing that all men may eaſily erre, and that no errours are ſo dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous as thoſe, which concerne religion; the Church ſhould be in a farre worſe caſe, then the meaneſt common-wealth (nay, almoſt then a denne of Theeues) if it were deſtitute of meanes, either to conuince hereſies, or to ſuppreſſe them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Novve it is no great labour to define, vvho vvas this chiefe and commander among the Apoſtles, and vvho after that time vvas, novve is, and muſt continue. Among the twelue Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles I doe not remember, that any <hi>Proteſtant</hi> preferreth any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther before Saint <hi>Peter;</hi> then Saint <hi>Hierome,</hi> and <hi>D. Couell</hi> aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring vs, <hi>that among them one was chiefe,</hi> vve may conclude it of Saint <hi>Peter.</hi> And this the rather, becauſe <hi>D. Sutcliffe</hi> vvriteth thus:<note n="g" place="margin">
                     <hi>Sutcl. ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſ. pag.</hi> 40.</note> Tertullian <hi>giueth the keyes only to</hi> Peter, <hi>ſaying: that the Church is built vpon him.</hi> And thus <hi>D. Sutcliffe</hi> teſtifieth for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe:<note n="h" place="margin">
                     <hi>Supr. pag.</hi> 3.</note> Peter <hi>preached in no place, but he there ordayned Biſhoppes and teachers, and founded Churches:</hi> vvhich in his booke againſt <hi>D. Kelliſon,</hi> he<note n="i" place="margin">
                     <hi>Sutcliffe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Kelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, pag.</hi> 105.</note> maketh an argument of ſupreamacy. <hi>D. Field</hi> telleth vs, from Scripture;<note n="k" place="margin">
                     <hi>Field p.</hi> 196</note> 
                  <hi>That Chriſt promiſed to build his Church vpon</hi> Saint <hi>Peter.</hi> Then no Chriſtian vvill doubt, (except hee vvill doubt of Chriſtes truth, and promiſes) but it vvas ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed.</p>
               <p>Concerning the ſupreamacie of the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty before acknowledgeth <hi>it to be our mother Church: and it was a rule</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Kings ſpeach confer. ſup.</note> 
                  <hi>to all, both in doctrine and ceremonies, when it was in her flouriſhing and</hi>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:15902:7"/> 
                  <hi>beſt eſtate.</hi> D. <hi>Couell</hi> writeth thus:<note n="l" place="margin">Couell def. of Hooker</note> 
                  <hi>The Church of</hi> Rome <hi>was the chiefe and only Church.</hi> M. <hi>Ormerod</hi>
                  <note n="m" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ormer. pict. pap. pag.</hi> 184.</note> calleth it <hi>the eye of the Weſt</hi> (in vvhich diuiſion <hi>England</hi> is) <hi>and the anker of piety.</hi> M. <hi>Downame</hi> graunteth<note n="n" place="margin">
                     <hi>Downame l.</hi> 2. <hi>Antich. pag.</hi> 105.</note> 
                  <hi>it was a note of a good Chriſtian, to cleane vnto the</hi> Roman <hi>Apoſtolicall Church.</hi> And thus both they, <hi>D. Sutcliffe</hi>
                  <note n="o" place="margin">
                     <hi>Sutcl. epiſt. dedicat. of ſubuerſ. and pag.</hi> 89.</note>, <hi>D. Field</hi>
                  <note n="p" place="margin">Field of the Church, &amp;c.</note>, and the reſt, doe ordinarily yeeld that it continued vntill the yeare of Chriſt ſix hundred and ſeauen, when <hi>Bonifacius</hi> Pope there, claimed (as they ſay) ſupreamacy firſt in the Church. <hi>D. Downames</hi> vvordes be:<note n="q" place="margin">
                     <hi>Downame lib.</hi> 1. <hi>pag.</hi> 4.</note> 
                  <hi>About the yeare of our Lord ſix hundred and ſeauen,</hi> Boniface <hi>the Pope and his Succeſſours, claymed and obtayned to be head of the</hi> Catholike <hi>or Vniuerſall Church.</hi> Then I thus demonſtrate from theſe <hi>Protestants,</hi> that this Church of <hi>Rome</hi> both claymed and exerciſed this ſupreame authority, vvhen it vvas in this <hi>flouriſhing and best eſtate, a rule to Churches of faith, anker of piety, &amp;c.</hi> Firſt, <hi>D. Sutcliffe</hi> is vvitneſſe;<note n="r" place="margin">
                     <hi>Sutcl. ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſ. pag.</hi> 57.</note> Ireneus <hi>ſaith, that euery Church ought to haue respect to the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>for her eminent principallity;</hi> vvhich vvas long before any generall Councell, or Chriſtian Emperour to giue or allowe this priuiledge. Secondly, <hi>D. Field</hi> plainely acknowledgeth;<note n="ſ" place="margin">
                     <hi>Field, lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 1.</note> that the ſupreamacy belonged to the Popes of <hi>Rome,</hi> before the firſt <hi>Nicen</hi> Councell. Then by the rules vvhich he giueth to knowe true Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions<note n="t" place="margin">
                     <hi>pa.</hi> 242. <hi>ſup.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>(cuſtome of the Church, conſent of Fathers, or an Apoſtolike Churches teſtimony)</hi> this muſt needes be of that kinde: And then e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall in authority vvith Scripture, as he acknowledgeth<note n="u" place="margin">
                     <hi>page</hi> 134.</note> of ſuch Traditions. <hi>M. Ormerod</hi> aſcendeth to Pope <hi>Anacletus,</hi> liuing with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in an hundred yeares of Chriſt; his wordes be theſe:<note n="x" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ormer. pict. pap. pag.</hi> 78.</note> 
                  <hi>To proue that the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>hath the preeminence ouer all Churches,</hi> Anacletus <hi>alleadgeth</hi> Math. 16. verſ. 18. <hi>Vpon this Rocke will I build my Church: and he expoundeth it thus:</hi> ſuper hanc Petram (id eſt) ſuper Eccleſiam Romanam, <hi>Vpon this Rocke: that is, vpon the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>will I build my Church.</hi> This is as great a clayme of ſupreamacy, and by as great vvarrant, as any Pope nowe claymeth it. Yet <hi>Anacletus</hi> vvas a Saint and holy Pope, euen in the <hi>best eſtate of that Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Againe, there were at thoſe daies accounted but three great parts of the world, <hi>Aſia, Africke,</hi> &amp; <hi>Europe:</hi> yet we are told by theſe <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants,</hi> that the Pope <hi>in that flouriſhing</hi> and vnſpotted time of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> claymed and exerciſed this ſupreamacy in all theſe parts. For <hi>Aſia</hi> (though in the <hi>Greeke</hi> Church) <hi>D. Couell</hi> telleth vs<note n="y" place="margin">
                     <hi>Couell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the plea of the Innoc. pa.</hi> 65.</note>, that Pope <hi>Victor</hi> in that time did authoritatiuely clayme ſupreamacy
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:15902:8"/> ouer all <hi>Aſia,</hi> excommunicating the Churches of it (to vſe his wordes) <hi>in ſeperating all</hi> Aſia <hi>from the vnity of the faithfull, for being diſobedient in the point and question of Eaſter.</hi> What greater ſupreama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy can be claymed in the Church, then to excommunicate and put forth of the Church, ſo great a part of the world?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>D. Downame</hi> yeeldeth to <hi>Bellarmine,</hi>
                  <note n="y" place="margin">
                     <hi>Downame lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Antich. pag.</hi> 105.</note> that <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> &amp; <hi>Victor Vti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſis</hi> in <hi>Africke</hi> vvere of opinion, <hi>that to adhere to the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>was a marke of a true</hi> Catholike <hi>in thoſe times:</hi> And <hi>M. Perkins</hi> ſaith:<note n="z" place="margin">
                     <hi>Per. problem pa.</hi> 237. 238.</note> 
                  <hi>Appeales were often made out of</hi> Africke <hi>to the Popes of</hi> Rome <hi>in thoſe dayes.</hi> Neither doth this Doctor denie,<note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Down. ſupr. pa.</hi> 106. 107.</note> but the Biſhops then <hi>did ſweare obedience to the Pope.</hi> And entreating of a Biſhop recanting his hereſies, he writeth of him in theſe wordes:<note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Down. ſupr. pag.</hi> 107.</note> 
                  <hi>He ſweareth to renounce his former hereſies, &amp; to profeſſe, &amp; maintayne that faith &amp; religion, which the Biſhoppe and Church of</hi> Rome <hi>did profeſſe. M. Ormerod</hi> witneſſeth,<note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ormerod ſupr. pag.</hi> 44.</note> that <hi>S. Leo</hi> taught, that God did aſſiſt and direct that See in decrees.</p>
               <p>Of <hi>Europe</hi> there can be no queſtion: for generally <hi>Proteſtants</hi> agree with <hi>D. Field</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">Field of the Church.</note>, <hi>D. Doue</hi>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">
                     <hi>Doue perſw. pag.</hi> 29. 30.</note>, <hi>D. Couell</hi>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">
                     <hi>Couel defen. of Hook. pag.</hi> 74. 75. 76.</note>, and <hi>M. Ormerod</hi>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ormer. pict. pap. pag.</hi> 184</note>, that the regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the <hi>Weſt</hi> Churches (among which this nation is) belonged to the Pope of <hi>Rome.</hi> And <hi>D. Sutcliffe</hi> giueth particuler examples,<note n="h" place="margin">
                     <hi>Sutcl. ſubu. pag.</hi> 19.</note> how <hi>S. Gregory</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded (to vſe his wordes) <hi>the Biſhops of France:</hi> &amp; commanded alſo in <hi>England the conſtituting of our Archbiſhop</hi> S. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine, <hi>and the very See of that preeminence at</hi> Canterbury. <hi>D. Couell</hi> vvriteth the ſame<note n="i" place="margin">
                     <hi>Cou. againſt Burges p.</hi> 49.</note> of Pope <hi>Gregories</hi> commanding authority in all <hi>Spayne:</hi> who prouoked by the hereſie of the <hi>Arrians,</hi> commanded <hi>that through all</hi> Spaine, <hi>there ſhould be but once dipping in Baptiſme.</hi> M. <hi>Middleton</hi> vvitneſſeth:<note n="k" place="margin">
                     <hi>Middleton papiſtomast. pag.</hi> 39.</note> that (at the leaſt) the firſt generall Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of <hi>Nice</hi> taught, <hi>the dignity of</hi> Rome <hi>ouer the</hi> Weſt <hi>Prouinces,</hi> (in which we of this nation are) and that <hi>by old cuſtome,</hi> which was, when that Church was <hi>in her beſt and flouriſhing eſtate, &amp; a rule to all.</hi> And to proue this cuſtome both larger, then ouer the <hi>Weſt</hi> (that is) vniuerſal ouer al Churches, and from the Apoſtles, he addeth thus:<note n="l" place="margin">
                     <hi>page</hi> 200.</note> 
                  <hi>Papias</hi> (liuing in the Apoſtles time) <hi>taught</hi> Peters <hi>primacy, &amp;</hi> Romiſh <hi>Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pality.</hi> And <hi>D. Downame</hi> writeth thus:<note n="m" place="margin">
                     <hi>Downame l.</hi> 1. <hi>Anticl riſt cap.</hi> 3. <hi>pa.</hi> 35.</note> 
                  <hi>Diuers Biſhops of</hi> Rome, <hi>before the time of</hi> Socrates <hi>the Hiſtorian</hi> (in that vnſpotted &amp; reguler time of that Church) <hi>contended to haue the primacy, ouer all other Churches: and that is the chiefe ſcope of many of their Epiſtles decretall.</hi> Neither doth <hi>D. Downame</hi>
                  <note n="n" place="margin">
                     <hi>page</hi> 36.</note> denie, but both <hi>Iuſtinian</hi> the Emperor, and the great ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Councell of <hi>Chalcedon,</hi> in the primatiue Church, attributed to
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:15902:8"/> the Pope of <hi>Rome, to be head of the Church;</hi> which he ſaith is the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt ſtile. And he addeth thus, of that Church, <hi>in that beſt eſtate: Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles of honour and preeminence were giuen to the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>as the chiefe or head of the Churches.</hi> And againe: <hi>Before the graunt of</hi> Phocas, <hi>the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>had the preeminence, and ſuperiority ouer all other Churches, excepting that of</hi> Conſtantinople. And both <hi>D. Field</hi>
                  <note n="o" place="margin">
                     <hi>Field lib.</hi> 1. <hi>of the Church<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi>
                  </note> telleth him abſolutely, that the Title of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> was but intruded, and vſurped: And when the firſt <hi>Nicen</hi> Councell gaue ſuch honour to the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, there was not ſo much as the name of <hi>Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople.</hi> And that this preeminence and ſuperiority, was a comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and binding authority, is proued before, from all parts of the world, wherein it was exerciſed, in <hi>that beſt and flouriſhing eſtate of that Church.</hi> That no Councell could be kept, none confirmed, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing concluded in the primatiue Church, without the Biſhoppe of <hi>Rome,</hi> his approbation wil approue in the chapter of Councels here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after. Wherefore, ſeing we haue beene taught before, by <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> that one primacy &amp; chiefe commanding authority, was euer neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary in the true Church of Chriſt: That <hi>S. Peter</hi> (as chiefe of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles) had, and exerciſed it in that time: And after him, the prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue and moſt ancient holy Popes of <hi>Rome</hi> (as ſucceſſors vnto him) euer claimed, exerciſed, and executed the ſame ſoueraigne ſpiritual Paſtorall office, and dignity ouer all Churches, in all parts of the world; and neither by Councell, Emperor, or ſuch Donation, but by old cuſtome and the inſtitution of Chriſt: And the ſame Church (as before) ſtill continueth the true Church of Chriſt: I hope it is no offence to agree with it, in this, as in other queſtions.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Chapter 4.</hi> All bookes receiued for Scripture, by the <hi>Roman</hi> Church are Canonicall.</head>
               <p>THus hauing (by the directions &amp; ſentence of <hi>Proteſtant</hi> writers, of ſo late memory as this preſent is) found out, that the <hi>Roman</hi> Church <hi>is the ſpouſe of Chriſt, his true Church, and piller of truth: whoſe communion we muſt embrace, followe her directions, reſt in her judgement, liuing &amp; dying therein to haue eternal life,</hi> the only and chiefeſt happy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes which we can ſeeke or find: And that the authority of the chiefe Biſhops of that holy &amp; Apoſtolike See, hath euer bin ſo ſoueraigne, chiefe, commanding, and ſupreame, as theſe men haue taught vs, in the former Chapters, we might here by <hi>D. Fields</hi> cenſure and aduiſe,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:15902:9"/> confine our ſelues, and vvade no further in ſo many intricate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſies of religion. But to giue a finall contentment to all curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities, let vs briefly enter into a particuler-like examination, of all principall Articles in queſtion: And firſt of Scriptures, vvhoſe au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority is either only, or chiefeſt with <hi>Proteſtants.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>D. Couell</hi> writeth in theſe wordes:<note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Couell def. of Hook. p.</hi> 31</note> 
                  <hi>The Church of</hi> Rome <hi>teacheth no bad opinion, to affirme that the Scriptures are holy, &amp; diuine in themſelues, but ſo eſteemed by vs for the authority of the Church.</hi> And againe: <hi>That the Scriptures are true, we haue it from the Church.</hi> And further thus:<note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>pag.</hi> 32. 33. <hi>ſupr.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>The Church hath foure ſinguler offices towardes the Scripture. Firſt, to be of them (as it were) a faithfull regiſter. Secondly, to diſcerue and judge be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene falſe and adulterate, and that which is true and perfect. The third, to publiſh and diuulge, to proclayme as a cryer, the true edict of our Lord him ſelfe. The laſt is, to be an Interpreter; and in that, following the ſafeſt rule (to make an vndiuided vnity of the truth vncapable of contradiction) to be a most faithfull expoſitor of his owne meaning.</hi> And concludeth thus:<note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>page</hi> 34. <hi>ſupr.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>We ſay, that we are taught to receiue the word of God, from the authority of the Church: we ſee her judgement, we heare her voice; &amp; in humility ſubſcribe vnto all this:</hi> Hitherto be <hi>D. Couels</hi> wordes, for the <hi>major</hi> propoſition of my Syllogiſme. But the <hi>minor</hi> or ſecond poſition, <hi>that the</hi> Roman <hi>Church is the true Church of Chriſt,</hi> is allowed, and proued by <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants</hi> before: Therefore this <hi>Proteſtant</hi> argument, muſt be thus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded. All bookes which the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> propoſeth for Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, the expoſitions which ſhee deliuereth, &amp;c. <hi>In humility we muſt ſubſcribe vnto them, receiue them as the word of God, from her authority.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>D. Doue</hi> referreth the queſtion, <hi>what bookes be Canonicall Scripture,</hi> to the two Doctors <hi>S. Auguſtine,</hi> and <hi>S. Hierome.</hi> His vvordes be theſe:<note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>Doue per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſ. pag.</hi> 15.</note> Catholikes <hi>proue them to be Canonicall out of</hi> S. Auguſtine: <hi>We, that they be</hi> Apocrypha <hi>out of</hi> S. Hierome, <hi>both which Doctors, are of no ſmall authority with the Church of</hi> Rome; <hi>and therefore in this we differ no more from them, then</hi> S. Hierome <hi>did from</hi> S. Auguſtine: Therefore (I hope) for many cauſes, <hi>Proteſtants</hi> will giue place vnto vs, in this queſtion. It is knowne, <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> in calling was aboue <hi>S. Hierome:</hi> In learning <hi>D. Couell</hi> telleth you,<note n="e" place="margin">
                     <hi>Cou. againſt Burg. pag.</hi> 3.</note> he was farre the moſt learned Doctor that euer was, or ſhall be in all likely-hood. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, your publike Conference<note n="f" place="margin">Conference, infr.</note> (to be after cited) hath anſwered <hi>S. Hieromes</hi> authority, for <hi>Catholikes.</hi> Fourthly, <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth in the name of the whole Church, for theſe bookes; his wordes
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:15902:9"/> be theſe:<note n="g" place="margin">
                     <hi>Auguſt. tom.</hi> 10. <hi>ſer.</hi> 191.</note> 
                  <hi>We receiue the old and newe Teſtament in that number of bookes, which the authority of the holy</hi> Catholike <hi>Church hath deliuered.</hi> And in the place where he deliuereth the Canon of Scriptures, as <hi>Catholikes</hi> nowe doe, hee giueth theſe rules, to him that vvould knowe vvhich bee true Scriptures; his vvordes bee theſe:<note n="h" place="margin">
                     <hi>Tom.</hi> 3. <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>doct. Chriſt cap.</hi> 8.</note> 
                  <hi>In Canonicall Scriptures let him followe the authority of the most</hi> Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like <hi>Churches, among which thoſe be which haue deſerued to haue A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolike Sees, and to receiue their Epiſtles:</hi> And ſo proceeding (too long to be cited) concludeth by all his rules, that all thoſe bookes vvhich the <hi>Roman</hi> Church nowe receiueth (there remembred by <hi>S. Auguſtine)</hi> are Canonicall.</p>
               <p>But to be briefe; The <hi>Protestant</hi> Surueyor of the communion booke affirmeth plainely:<note n="i" place="margin">
                     <hi>Suruey of the booke of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon prayer, pag.</hi> 27. 28. 29. 30. 31.</note> that <hi>the</hi> Proteſtants <hi>of</hi> England <hi>muſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue for Canonicall, theſe bookes with the</hi> Roman <hi>Church.</hi> So like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe doe the 22. Preachers of <hi>London</hi> in their Petition<note n="k" place="margin">
                     <hi>Petit. of</hi> 22. <hi>preachers ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept. againſt homilies, and except.</hi> 4. <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the com. booke.</hi>
                  </note>. And <hi>D. Field</hi> is of the ſame opinion, or muſt be; for thus he vvriteth:<note n="l" place="margin">
                     <hi>Field lib.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 23. <hi>pa.</hi> 245.</note> 
                  <hi>The an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient and true beleeuing</hi> Iewes <hi>before the comming of Chriſt (especially ſuch as liued in</hi> Greece, <hi>and nations out of</hi> Iury, <hi>commonly called</hi> Helle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts) <hi>receiued thoſe bookes for Canonicall Scripture.</hi> And (to vſe his vvordes) <hi>Hence it came to paſſe, that the</hi> Iewes <hi>deliuered a double Canon of Scripture, to the Chriſtian Churches.</hi> And ſpeaking againe of that volume of the <hi>Helleniſts,</hi> he addeth:<note n="m" place="margin">
                     <hi>page</hi> 246.</note> 
                  <hi>Theſe bookes joyned in one volume, were tranſlated out of</hi> Greeke <hi>into</hi> Latin, <hi>and read by them of the</hi> Latin <hi>Church in that tranſlation.</hi> And entreating of <hi>S. Augustine</hi> and the <hi>Latin</hi> Fathers (eſpecially in <hi>Africke)</hi> and the third <hi>Carthaginian</hi> Councell, vvhere this Canon is receiued, he vvriteth thus: <hi>They reckon the bookes of Scripture, according as they found them in vſe in the</hi> Latin <hi>Church.</hi> Then <hi>D. Field</hi> hath abſolutely graunted that in the <hi>Latin</hi> Church (vnder vvhich <hi>England</hi> is) theſe Scriptures vvere euer eſteemed for Canonicall. And being tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated (as he acknowledgeth) out of <hi>Greeke</hi> into <hi>Latin,</hi> this <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian</hi> vvill not eaſily perſvvade, but the <hi>Greeke</hi> Church alſo firſt embraced them; for he ſaith thus:<note n="n" place="margin">
                     <hi>page</hi> 245. <hi>ſupr.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>The</hi> Greeke Iewes, <hi>or</hi> Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leniſts, <hi>deliuered this Canon to the Chriſtian Churches;</hi> then firſt to the <hi>Greeke</hi> Church, being in <hi>Greece</hi> among them, and beſt vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding thoſe <hi>Greeke</hi> Scriptures, before they vvere tranſlated into <hi>Latin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Protestant</hi> Conference at <hi>Hampton-Court,</hi> entreating
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:15902:10"/> of the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> exceptions againſt theſe Scriptures, vſeth theſe wordes:<note n="o" place="margin">
                     <hi>Conference, pag.</hi> 60.</note> 
                  <hi>Most of the objections made againſt thoſe bookes, were the old cauils of the</hi> Iewes, <hi>renewed by</hi> S. Hierome <hi>in his time, who was the firſt that gaue them the name of</hi> Apocrypha: <hi>which opinion vpon</hi> Ruffinus <hi>his challendge, he after a ſort diſclaimed; the rather, becauſe a generall offence was taken at his ſpeaches in that kinde.</hi> Hitherto the cenſure of that pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like conference, vvhereby the ground of <hi>Proteſtants</hi> denying theſe bookes by <hi>S. Hieromes</hi> opinion (as <hi>D. Doue</hi> hath witneſſed) is vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ouerthrowne. <hi>D. Couell</hi> anſwereth<note n="p" place="margin">
                     <hi>Couell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Burges pag.</hi> 85. 86. 87. 88. 89. 90. 91.</note> the objections againſt <hi>Burges</hi> the <hi>Puritan,</hi> in particuler as <hi>Catholikes</hi> doe: and ſheweth, that theſe bookes haue vvithout cauſe, beene accuſed of faults by <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> only to denie them to be Canonicall, as <hi>Catholikes</hi> hold. He addeth further thus: <hi>They are moſt true, and might haue there concilement of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Scriptures.</hi> And againe in theſe vvordes:<note n="q" place="margin">
                     <hi>Couell ſupr. pag.</hi> 87.</note> 
                  <hi>If</hi> Ruffinus <hi>be not deceiued, they were approued as parts of the old Teſtament, by the Apoſtles. For when</hi> S. Hierome <hi>write ſo ſcornefully of the hiſtory of</hi> Suſanna, <hi>and the ſong of the three children, he chargeth him therein, to haue robbed the treaſure of the holy Ghoſt, and diuine inſtrument, which the Apoſtles deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered to the Churches. And</hi> S. Hierome <hi>(who is not vſually ſlowe to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend himſelfe) leaueth that point vnanſwered, pretending that what he had ſpoken, was not as his owne opinion, but what the</hi> Iewes <hi>objected. And for his paines in tranſlating the booke of</hi> Iudith, (vvhich the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie) <hi>he giueth this reaſon; becauſe we reade, that the Councell of</hi> Nice <hi>did reckon it in the number of holy Scriptures:</hi> Hitherto <hi>D. Couels</hi> vvordes. And much like vnto this of <hi>Ruffinus,</hi> he citeth<note n="r" place="margin">
                     <hi>pag.</hi> 76. 77.</note> from <hi>S. Auguſtine, S. Cyprian,</hi> and others, <hi>temporibus Apoſtolorum proximis, in the next age to the Apoſtles.</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Objection </seg>
                  </label> And if any man ſhall object againſt me, that<note n="ſ" place="margin">
                     <hi>Art.</hi> 6. <hi>Syn. Lond.</hi> 1562.</note> the ſixt Article of the <hi>Engliſh Proteſtant</hi> religion, excepteth againſt theſe bookes, and leaueth them forth of the Canon of Scriptures:<note n="t" place="margin">Anſwere.</note> I anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>were; this proueth nothing, but to proue their religion to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictory, and vnpoſſible to be true. For the bookes of Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and Homilies (as before) authorized aſwell by thoſe Articles, as the ſtatute of Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and the late <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Canons, receiue, cite, and practiſe them for Canonicall. Againe, that ſixt Article is contradictory to it ſelfe, in this point (and ſo of no autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity by <hi>Proteſtants</hi> themſelues:) for it only approueth for Canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Scriptures (to vſe the wordes of the Article)<note n="u" place="margin">
                     <hi>Articul.</hi> 6. <hi>ſupr.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Thoſe Canonicall bookes of the old and newe Teſtament (of whoſe authority was neuer any</hi>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:15902:10"/> 
                  <hi>doubt in the Church) in the name of holy Scriptures, theſe we vnderſtand.</hi> And yet theſe <hi>Proteſtants</hi> doe tell vs<note n="x" place="margin">
                     <hi>Willet Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nopſ. q.</hi> 1. <hi>of Script. pag.</hi> 2. 3. <hi>edit. anno.</hi> 1594.</note> that all Scriptures haue beene doubted off, by one Church or other. But, to contaynemy ſelfe vvithin my time of limitation, I vvill only cite the Biſhop of <hi>Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter;</hi> he writeth thus:<note n="y" place="margin">
                     <hi>B. Bilſon ſur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uey of Chriſts ſufferings, pag.</hi> 664.</note> 
                  <hi>The Scriptures themſelues were not fully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued in all places, no not in</hi> Euſebius <hi>time. He ſaith the Epiſtle of</hi> Iames, <hi>of</hi> Iude, <hi>the ſecond of</hi> Peter, <hi>the ſecond and third of</hi> Iohn, <hi>are contradicted. Thè Epiſtle to the</hi> Hebrewes <hi>was contradicted: the Churches of</hi> Syria <hi>did not receiue the ſecond Epiſtle of</hi> Peter, <hi>nor the ſecond and third of</hi> Iohn, <hi>nor the Epiſtle of</hi> Iude, <hi>nor the</hi> Apocalipſe; <hi>the like might be ſaid for the Churches of</hi> Arabia. <hi>Will you hence conclude, that theſe parts of Scripture were not Apoſtolike, or that we neede not receiue them nowe, becauſe they were formerly doubted off?</hi> Hitherto <hi>B. Bilſons</hi> vvordes: By which, it both appeareth by <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> howe their Article doth contradict it ſelfe. And I may conclude (vvith the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) that all bookes which the <hi>Roman</hi> Church receiueth for Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, be Canonicall and moſt holy. Whereby it is too manifeſt, what a grounded religion, that <hi>Proteſtancy</hi> is, which hath excluded, ſo long time, ſo many bookes of Scripture, and ſo many Articles of faith, <hi>prayer for the dead, patronage of Saints and Angels, prayers vnto them and the like:</hi> And yet would pretend, that their religion is only founded vpon the word of God in Scripture.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Chapter 5.</hi> The vulgar <hi>Latin</hi> tranſlation of Scriptures vſed by the <hi>Roman</hi> Church is beſt: the <hi>Engliſh Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant</hi> tranſlations are erroneous.</head>
               <p>NEXT to the Canon and Text of Scriptures, let vs entreate of their tranſlations, both as they are vſed in the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, and the <hi>Engliſh Proteſtants.</hi> And firſt, concerning the vulgar <hi>Latin</hi> allowed among <hi>Catholikes, D. Doue</hi> writeth thus:<note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Doue per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion. p.</hi> 16</note> 
                  <hi>We</hi> (Proteſtants) <hi>graunt it fit, that for vniformity in quotations of places, in ſchooles and pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pits, one</hi> Latin <hi>text ſhould be vſed, and we can be contented for the antiquity thereof, to preferre the old vulgar tranſlation, before all other</hi> Latin <hi>bookes; ſo much we doe yeeld to the Councell of</hi> Trent.</p>
               <p>And <hi>D. Couell</hi> entreating of tranſlations of Scripture, againſt <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges</hi> the <hi>Puritan,</hi> anſwereth in theſe wordes:<note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Couell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, pag.</hi> 94.</note> 
                  <hi>We are ready to confeſſe,</hi>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:15902:11"/> 
                  <hi>whether you vnderſtand the</hi> Italian, <hi>or that which goeth vnder the name of</hi> S. Hierome, <hi>that they were vſed anciently in the Church, a thouſand and three hundred yeares agoe, one of them by</hi> S. Auguſtine <hi>preferred be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all the reſt, the other highly commended by</hi> Beza, <hi>and that of the vulgar (though with</hi> Pagnin <hi>and</hi> Driëdo) <hi>we thinke it was not</hi> S. Hieromes, <hi>but mixt; yet we can be content, to ſay as</hi> Iſodore <hi>doth of it,</hi> interpretatio eius, <hi>this tranſlation is to be preferred before others:</hi> Hitherto his owne wordes. And if <hi>M. Couell, Doue,</hi> and other <hi>Proteſtants</hi> well conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the judgement of the Councell of <hi>Trent,</hi> in this queſtion, and the preface to the Bible of <hi>Xiſtus quintus,</hi> they ſhall perceiue the intent of the holy Councell, being only to approue that <hi>Latin</hi> tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation, <hi>vſed a thouſand and three hundred yeares ſince in the Church</hi> (as <hi>D. Couell</hi> telleth vs) when it was <hi>in the flouriſhing and beſt eſtate;</hi> and ſo to be reuerenced by <hi>Proteſtants</hi> judgement before; and not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject either the <hi>Greeke</hi> in the newe, or <hi>Hebrewe</hi> Text of the old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament.</p>
               <p>Touching other tranſlations, <hi>D. Couell</hi> writeth:<note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>Couel ſupr. pag.</hi> 94.</note> 
                  <hi>No tranſlation whatſoeuer, is authenticall Scripture.</hi> And <hi>D. Doue</hi> addeth:<note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>Doue perſw pag.</hi> 16.</note> 
                  <hi>All tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlations haue many faultes.</hi> M. <hi>Burges</hi> in his Apologie writeth thus, of the approued <hi>Engliſh Proteſtant</hi> tranſlation:<note n="e" place="margin">
                     <hi>Burges A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polog. pa.</hi> 93. <hi>in D. Couels anſwere.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>It is a tranſlation which hath many omiſsions, many additions, which ſome-times obſcureth, ſome-times peruerteth the ſence; being ſome-time ſenſeleſſe, ſome-times contrary.</hi> And <hi>D. Couell</hi> in his anſwere acknowledgeth, ſo farre faults in their tranſlation, that he requireth a better to be eſtabliſhed. The 22. Preachers of <hi>London</hi> write of the tranſlation only in the commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion booke, in this manner:<note n="f" place="margin">
                     <hi>Petit. of</hi> 22. <hi>preachers ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept.</hi> 11. <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the com. booke.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>It contayneth in it diuers corrupt tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Scriptures, by leauing out of wordes, putting too of wordes, peruer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the meaning of the holy Ghoſt.</hi> The <hi>Suruey</hi> of the booke of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon prayer, addeth:<note n="g" place="margin">
                     <hi>Suruey of the booke of com. prayer, pag.</hi> 160.</note> 
                  <hi>There be many groſſe corruptions, as may partly appeare by the Abridgement of the Miniſters of</hi> Lincolne <hi>Dyoceſſe.</hi> The <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Authour of the <hi>Aduertiſement</hi> teſtifieth:<note n="h" place="margin">
                     <hi>Aduertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, an.</hi> 1604</note> 
                  <hi>The Bible is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted in</hi> 848. <hi>places in the old Teſtament. The</hi> Engliſh Proteſtant <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, is inferior to the</hi> Turkes <hi>Alcaron.</hi> And ſo, <hi>Chriſtianity is denyed in</hi> England <hi>by publike authority.</hi> Therefore moſt juſtly might his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty ſay in the publike conference:<note n="i" place="margin">
                     <hi>Conference, pag.</hi> 46.</note> 
                  <hi>That he could neuer yet ſee a Bible well tranſlated into</hi> Engliſh; <hi>but the worſt of all he thought the</hi> Geneua <hi>to be.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:15902:11"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Chapter 6.</hi> The true, lawfull, and juridicall expoſition of Scriptures, is in the <hi>Roman</hi> Church; and not with <hi>Proteſtants.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE true and vvarranted expoſition of Scriptures, is abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proued before, to belong to the true Church of Chriſt, and the <hi>Roman</hi> Church. For this place, <hi>D. Field</hi> vvriteth thus:<note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Field lib.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 19. <hi>pa.</hi> 134.</note> 
                  <hi>We confeſſe, that neither conference of places, nor conſideration of the</hi> Antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentia, <hi>and</hi> Conſequentia, <hi>nor looking into the originals, are of any force, vnleſſe we finde the thinges, which we conceiue to be vnderſtood and meant, in the places interpreted, to be conſonant to the rule of faith.</hi> And this <hi>rule of faith</hi> as he further teacheth,<note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>page</hi> 242.</note> muſt be tryed either <hi>by the generall practiſe of the Church, the renowmed of all ages, or the Paſtors of an Apoſtolike Church:</hi> vvhich (as the vvorld can vvitneſſe) no <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant</hi> can make clayme vnto. Therefore as <hi>D. Couell</hi> vvriteth:<note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>Couell def. of Hooker. pag.</hi> 85.</note> 
                  <hi>Doctrines deriued, exhortations deducted, interpretations agreeable are not the word of God.</hi> And yet theſe be the groundes of <hi>Proteſtant</hi> religion, and thoſe vvhereupon their pretended faith and juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion it ſelfe, vvith them dependeth; Although <hi>D. Field</hi> thus againe condemneth it:<note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>Field p.</hi> 226</note> 
                  <hi>Priuate interpretation is not ſo propoſed and vrged, as if they would binde all others to receiue it.</hi> Therefore he aſſigneth<note n="e" place="margin">
                     <hi>page</hi> 228.</note> three kindes of interpretation and judgement: <hi>One of diſcretion common to all; the other of direction in the Paſtours of the Church; and a third, of juriſdiction proper to them that haue ſupreame power in the Church.</hi> And this third hee only acknowledgeth in <hi>the Biſhops aſſembled in a generall Councell, which</hi> (as he teacheth) <hi>may interpret the Scripture, and by their authority ſuppreſſe all them, that gaine-ſay ſuch interpretation, and ſubject euery man (that ſhall diſobey ſuch deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations as they conſent vpon) to excommunication and cenſures of like nature:</hi> Hitherto his vvordes. Nowe that there neither hath beene, nor poſſibly can bee, any generall Councell among <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> (none clayming further juriſdiction, then their owne temporall Terrytories) it is both apparant to all, and acknovvledged<note n="f" place="margin">
                     <hi>Relation of relig. cap.</hi> 47.</note> in expreſſe vvordes by the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Relator of religion. And yet beſides <hi>D. Field</hi> recited before, <hi>D. Sutcliffe</hi>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">
                     <hi>Sutcl. ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſ. pa.</hi> 119.</note>, <hi>D. Morton</hi>
                  <note n="h" place="margin">
                     <hi>Morton e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. dedicat.</hi> 2. <hi>part. Apol. lib.</hi> 4. 2. <hi>part. Apol. pa.</hi> 340 <hi>cap.</hi> 18.</note>, <hi>M. Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let</hi>
                  <note n="i" place="margin">Willet An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilog.</note> and the reſt acknowledge ordinarily, that <hi>a generall Councell</hi> hath the higheſt and binding judgement. And although <hi>M. Willet</hi>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:15902:12"/> doth ſay,<note n="k" place="margin">
                     <hi>Willet pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fat. Engl. &amp; Antilog. pag.</hi> 71. 120.</note> 
                  <hi>That in</hi> England <hi>the temporall Prince is Gouernour, ruler, chiefe ouerſeer and ſteward of the Church, to whoſe judgement and redreſſe the reformation of religion belongeth;</hi> Yet he addeth:<note n="l" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 150. <hi>&amp;</hi> 43. <hi>ſupr.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Neither he nor their Church hath any priuiledge from errour:</hi> But plainely proteſteth,<note n="m" place="margin">Willet pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fa. to the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in Antilo.</note> 
                  <hi>They muſt take out a newe leſſon; and learne to reforme their erroneous conceits.</hi> And more then this is generally taught, and confeſſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them; of which hereafter. For this time and place I will on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly make exemplification, of <hi>D. Doue</hi> his graunt, and confeſſion; vvhich followeth in theſe vvordes:<note n="n" place="margin">
                     <hi>D. Doue per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſ. pag.</hi> 31.</note> 
                  <hi>When the Maſſe was firſt put downe, King</hi> Henry <hi>had his</hi> Engliſh <hi>Lyturgie, and that was judged abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute without exception: but when King</hi> Edward <hi>came to the Crowne, that was condemned, and an other in the place which</hi> Peter Martir, <hi>and</hi> Bucer <hi>did approue, as very conſonant to Gods word. When Queene</hi> Elizabeth <hi>beganne her raigne, the former was judged to be full of imperfections, and a newe was deuiſed, and allowed by the conſent of the Clergie: but about the middle of her raigne, we grewe weary of that booke, and great meanes haue beene wrought to abandon that, and eſtabliſh an other, which although it was not obtayned; yet we doe (at the leaſt, at euery change of Prince) change our booke of common prayers, we be ſo wanton, that we knowe not what we would haue:</hi> Hitherto his wordes; and he freely confeſſeth errours in all theſe ſtates and changes. Yet this flitting from errour to er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, finding no center, hath beene ſo grieuous euen to ſome <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants,</hi> that the <hi>Suruey</hi> of the booke of common prayer, vſeth theſe wordes:<note n="o" place="margin">
                     <hi>Suruey of the commun. booke, pag.</hi> 159. 160.</note> 
                  <hi>The late Archbiſhop of</hi> Canterbury <hi>(as is credibly reported) tooke ſuch a griefe</hi> (when the communion booke ſhould haue beene altered) <hi>diſcouered by theſe or like wordes; good Lord! when ſhall we knowe what to truſt vnto? that he preſently fell into his palſey, was carryed from the Court, and dyed ſhortly after.</hi> But let any man enter into a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious conſideration of <hi>Proteſtant</hi> doctrine in this point; that vnder paine of damnation vve are bound, to finde and followe the truth; That generall Councels (as before) may ſubject <hi>euery man diſobeying their determinations, to excommunication and cenſures of like nature,</hi> the moſt terrible and fearefull puniſhment of this world; And <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants</hi> in <hi>England</hi> ſo ſeuerely puniſh all <hi>Catholikes,</hi> for not conſenting to their religion, which themſelues thus loade with errours; and all judgements <hi>Eccleſiaſticall,</hi> euen generall Councels<note n="p" place="margin">
                     <hi>Articul.</hi> 21. <hi>anno</hi> 1562.</note> 
                  <hi>may erre and haue erred, euen in thinges pertayning vnto God,</hi> as is defined in their Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, and is commonly taught and beleeued with them, to excuſe
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:15902:12"/> their errours. This conſideration is able, to putmen (not regard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe of ſaluation) into more then a quaking palſey.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Chapter 7.</hi> Traditions are of equall authority with Scripture: yet proue <hi>Catholike</hi> religion.</head>
               <p>THE dignity and authority of vnwritten and Apoſtolicall Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions (being lawfully proued) was euer eſteemed ſuch, that <hi>M. Wotton</hi> affirmeth:<note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Wotton def. of Perkins. pag.</hi> 405.</note> 
                  <hi>Out of all queſtion we are bound to keepe them.</hi> And telleth,<note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>page</hi> 436.</note> 
                  <hi>That</hi> M. Perkins <hi>was of the ſame opinion.</hi>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>Field p.</hi> 134</note> 
                  <hi>D. Field</hi> ſpeaketh of ſuch Traditions in theſe vvordes: <hi>There is no reaſon but theſe ſhould be equall with the Scriptures. For it is not the writing, that giueth theſe thinges their authority, but the worth and credit of him that deliuereth them, though by word and liuely voice only.</hi> He addeth alſo,<note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>Field p.</hi> 240</note> that <hi>the perpetuall Virginity of our Lady was a Tradition,</hi> and only re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued by ſuch authority, and ſo doe other <hi>Proteſtants.</hi> And both they and <hi>D. Field</hi>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">Field ſupr.</note> acknowledge <hi>Heluidius</hi> was condemned of hereſie (and juſtly) for denyall thereof: which could not be, except to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie the doctrine of true Traditions, were to denie the word of God, in their judgements.</p>
               <p>Nowe let vs ſee, vvhat Traditions we ſhall haue approued by <hi>Proteſtants:</hi> The ſame Authour maketh this diſcourſe and diuiſion following:<note n="f" place="margin">
                     <hi>Field lib.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <hi>cap.</hi> 19.</note> 
                  <hi>First, we receiue the number and names of the Authours of bookes, diuine and Canonicall, as deliuered by Tradition. This Tradition we admit: the number, authours, and integrity of the partes of theſe bookes, we receiue as deliuered by Tradition.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The ſecond kinde of Tradition which we admit, is that ſummary com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of the chiefe heades of Chriſtian doctrine, contayned in the Creede of the Apoſtles, which was deliuered to the Church, as a rule of faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The third, is that forme of Chriſtian doctrine and explication of the ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall partes thereof, which the firſt Chriſtians receiuing of the ſame Apoſtles, that deliuered to them the Scriptures, commended to poſterities. This may rightly be tearmed a Tradition: for that we neede a playne and diſtinct ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of many thinges, which are ſome-what obſcurely contayned in the Scriptures.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">
                     <hi>Field p.</hi> 239</note> 
                  <hi>The fourth kinde of Tradition, is the continued practiſe of ſuch thinges, as neither are contayned in the Scripture expreſſely, nor the example of ſuch</hi>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:15902:13"/> 
                  <hi>practiſe expreſſely there deliuered, though the groundes, reaſons, and cauſes of the neceſsity of ſuch practiſe he there contayned.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note n="h" place="margin">
                     <hi>p.</hi> 239 <hi>ſupr.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>The fift kinde of Traditions, comprehendeth ſuch obſeruations, as in particuler are not commanded in Scripture, nor the neceſsity of them from thence concluded,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, comming to Traditions, touching conuerſation and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, he preuenteth &amp; confuteth the vſuall objections of <hi>Proteſtants</hi> about this doctrine, in theſe wordes:<note n="i" place="margin">
                     <hi>Field pag.</hi> 241. 242.</note> 
                  <hi>That the Apoſtles deliuered ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thinges of this nature to the Churches; ſome by way of precept, ſome by way of counſaile and aduiſe only; ſome to particuler Churches, and ſome to all; ſome to continue but for a time, and ſome to continue for euer, we make no doubt.</hi> And exemplifying, that the <hi>Lordes day or Sonday</hi> is of this kinde, he addeth:<note n="k" place="margin">
                     <hi>Field ſupr. pag.</hi> 242.</note> 
                  <hi>And ſundry other thinges there are, which doubtleſſe the Apoſtles deliuered by Tradition; but they are confounded with</hi> Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall <hi>Traditions (as</hi> Waldenſis <hi>aptly noteth) that we might the more reuerence the conſtitutions of the Church, and are dispenſable by the guides of the Church:</hi> Hitherto be the wordes of <hi>D. Field.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then to make aſhort reflexion vpon this his doctrine: By his firſt rule of Traditions, he muſt needes graunt vnto vs (which I haue proued before at large) that althoſe bookes which the <hi>Roman</hi> church approueth for Scripture, together with the ſpeciall doctrines, of prayer for the dead, to Angels, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are Traditions. For not only <hi>D. Field</hi> and his rules, doe ſo aſſure vs; but <hi>D. Couell</hi>
                  <note n="l" place="margin">
                     <hi>Couell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, pag.</hi> 87.</note> from the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matiue Church hath told vs, that all which we receiue, <hi>were the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the holy Ghoſt, and diuine inſtrument, which the Apoſtles deliuered to the Churches.</hi> Secondly, we muſt of neceſſity reſort to the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, to knowe and learne <hi>the forme of Chriſtian doctrine, and expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the ſeuerall parts thereof, and the obſcurities of Scriptures.</hi> For he ſaith, that the Apoſtles deliuered this <hi>as a Tradition to poſterities:</hi> And no poſterity of <hi>Proteſtants</hi> can be of this poſterity; becauſe both their <hi>priorities &amp; poſterities,</hi> denie Traditions. Thirdly, <hi>D. Field</hi> muſt needes ſeeke for, or allowe of many Traditions, which he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membreth not; and in all equall judgement, as many Articles of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike</hi> religion, as we claime by Tradition: for in his fourth, fift, and ſixt member of Traditions, he euer ſpeaketh<note n="m" place="margin">
                     <hi>Field pag.</hi> 241. 242.</note> of them in the plurall number; as, <hi>thinges, obſeruations, of this ſort, ſundry other,</hi> and the like. And yet, he only recounteth <hi>baptiſme of Infants</hi> in the fourth<note n="n" place="margin">
                     <hi>page</hi> 239.</note>: <hi>The ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation of Lent</hi> in the fift<note n="o" place="margin">
                     <hi>page</hi> 239.</note>: and <hi>Sonday,</hi> or the <hi>Lordes day,</hi> in the laſt.
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:15902:13"/> If he will ſay, they are confounded with <hi>Eccleſiaſticall</hi> Traditions (as he did) <hi>that men might more reuerence the conſtitutions of the Church:</hi> Let them at the laſt, recant their contempt and diſlike againſt them. And this the rather, becauſe the rules vvhich he aſſigneth to knowe true Traditions, (being<note n="p" place="margin">
                     <hi>Field p.</hi> 242</note> 
                  <hi>the authority and cuſtome of the Church, conſent of Fathers, or teſtimony of an Apoſtlike Church)</hi> neither doe, nor poſſibly can tell, of any Traditions to aduantage <hi>Protestants,</hi> which denie all Traditions: So that of neceſſity both the Traditions, and rules to knowe them, doe, and muſt belong to the Church Apoſtolike of <hi>Rome,</hi> being in this queſtion a rule of it ſelfe, as he hath declared.</p>
               <p>Then by the doctrine of <hi>D. Field,</hi> and the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> before (and nowe to be cited) <hi>Catholikes</hi> may lawfully ſay, with the ancient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, with <hi>D. Couell</hi>
                  <note n="q" place="margin">
                     <hi>Cou. againſt Burges, pag.</hi> 139. 124. 125</note>, and other <hi>Proteſtants: That the ſigne of the Croſſe, is an Apoſtolicall conſtitution and Tradition.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>With <hi>D. Couel</hi>
                  <note n="r" place="margin">
                     <hi>pa.</hi> 122. <hi>ſup.</hi>
                  </note> againe, and the ancient Fathers, &amp; from them: that the <hi>mixture of water with wine in the Euchariſt, is an Apoſtolical Tradition.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>With the Paſtors of the Apoſtolike Churches, three hundred Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and conſent and cuſtome of the Church <hi>(D. Fields</hi> rules for true Traditions) in the ſecond <hi>Nicen</hi> Councell<note n="ſ" place="margin">
                     <hi>Conc. Nic.</hi> 2.</note>: <hi>That reuerence of Images is an Apoſtolicall Tradition.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>With <hi>S. Chriſoſtome, S. Auguſtine,</hi> and <hi>S. Epiphanius,</hi> by <hi>D. Fields</hi> rules, and <hi>M. Middletons</hi>
                  <note n="t" place="margin">
                     <hi>Middleton Papiſtomast. pag.</hi> 137. 138 47. 45.</note> graunt: <hi>That ſacrifice and prayer for the dead, was an Apoſtolicall Tradition.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>With the ancient Fathers, ſo receiuing from thoſe vvhich vvent before them, by graunt alſo of <hi>M. Middleton:</hi>
                  <note n="u" place="margin">
                     <hi>pa.</hi> 134. <hi>ſup.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>That vowes of chaſtity, and ſingle life in Prieſtes, is to be obſerued by Tradition.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>With the ancient Fathers: that Reliques to be reuerenced, is a Tradition, when <hi>M. Willet</hi>
                  <note n="x" place="margin">
                     <hi>Willet Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>log. pag.</hi> 13.</note> telleth vs, that <hi>Vigilantius</hi> was condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of hereſie, for denying it.</p>
               <p>With his Majeſty<note n="y" place="margin">
                     <hi>Conference. pag.</hi> 13.</note> and the conference (with the conſent of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, Apoſtolike Churches, &amp;c.) <hi>That the particuler and perſonal abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution from ſinne after confeſsion, is Apoſtolicall and a very Godly ordinance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>With the <hi>Proteſtant</hi>
                  <note n="z" place="margin">
                     <hi>Conference, ſupr. pag.</hi> 18.</note> Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter</hi> (antiquity ſo conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting:) <hi>That baptiſme to be miniſtred by priuate perſons in time of neceſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, is an holy Tradition.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>With his Majeſty and the ſaid conference:<note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Conference, pag.</hi> 35. 36.</note> that <hi>Biſhops he diuinae ordinationis.</hi> With the ſame <hi>Proteſtant</hi> conference,<note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Conference, pag.</hi> 10. 11.</note> and antiquity: not only that <hi>Confirmation is an Apoſtolicall Tradition;</hi> But (becauſe it
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:15902:14"/> is ſo joyned by them with Baptiſme, and hath both <hi>a viſible ſigne,</hi> and grace, by the Communion booke<note n="c" place="margin">Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>m. booke tit. Confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> reuiued) that it is <hi>a Sacrament by Tradition.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>With the ancient Father <hi>S. Baſil,</hi> M. <hi>Wotton</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>Wotton def. of Perkins, p.</hi> 465. 466.</note> ſo aſſuring vs of his opinion: that <hi>the very profeſsion of our faith, by which we beleeue in the</hi> Father, <hi>the</hi> Sonne, <hi>and the holy</hi> Ghoſt, <hi>is a Tradition.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>With <hi>D. Ceuell:</hi>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">
                     <hi>Cou. againſt the plea of the Innoc. p.</hi> 104.</note> 
                  <hi>That it was an Apoſtolicall Tradition or Ordination, to ordayne Archbiſhops in their Prouinces; as Biſhops alſo in their Dioceſſe, to rule the Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>With the Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter</hi>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">
                     <hi>B. Bilſons Suruey of Chriſts ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, p.</hi> 664.</note> againſt the <hi>Puritans:</hi> that the <hi>Article of Chriſtes diſcent to hell,</hi> and the <hi>Creede</hi> wherein it is contay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, <hi>is an Apostolicall Tradition, deliuered to the Church, by the direction and agreement of the Apoſtles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And to conclude briefly: why may not we ſay with the Councell of <hi>Florence,</hi> cited by <hi>M. Willet</hi>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">
                     <hi>Willet Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nop. contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſ.</hi> 1. <hi>q.</hi> 7.</note> for generall, and the Patriarkes of the Apoſtolike Sees there preſent, with the Councell of <hi>Conſtance,</hi> not of vnequal authority, and the Councel of <hi>Trent</hi> (to paſſe others) with ſix Cardinals, foure Legates, three Patriarkes, two and thirty Archbiſhops, two hundred twenty eight Biſhops, and fiue Abbots there aſſembled (as <hi>D. Doue</hi> telleth vs) that <hi>Proteſtancy</hi> in all points is falſe, and <hi>Catholike</hi> religion true: when no <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Church can ſhewe any one ſuch like authority for their cauſe? And this of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity <hi>D. Field</hi> with his <hi>Proteſtants</hi> muſt acknowledge, or freely by their recited doctrine confeſſe; that there neither is, nor can be hereafter by his rules, true and certayne Scripture, Tradition, or Religion in the world. For if we neither haue Scripture, expoſition of the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties in it, or Tradition, but by Tradition (as he hath graunted) and thoſe only three rules to knowe them: if thoſe rules may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe vnto vs falſe Scriptures, falſe expoſitions of their obſcurities, and falſe Traditions in matters of faith; faith cannot be certayne, and religion grounded vpon it, is ouerthrowne.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Chapter 8.</hi> Of the authority, and commanding higheſt power of gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Councels: prouing the doctrine of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church.</head>
               <p>IT may ſufficiently be gathered, by that which hath beene entrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted before, both that generall Councels are of higheſt authority
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:15902:14"/> in the Church of Chriſt, and their teſtimony for <hi>Catholike</hi> religion. Therefore to be briefe in this queſtion; concerning their chiefeſt judgement and preeminence: firſt, the Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter</hi> writeth thus:<note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>B. Bilſ. Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uey of Chriſts ſuffer. pa.</hi> 83.</note> 
                  <hi>The authority of generall Councels, is moſt holſome in the Church;</hi> and citeth <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> to that purpoſe. <hi>D. Morton</hi> writeth,<note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Morto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> part.</hi> 2. <hi>Apol. pag.</hi> 340. <hi>l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 18</note> 
                  <hi>That</hi> concilium publicum eſt ſummus judex: <hi>a generall Councell is higheſt judge.</hi> The <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Relator of religion is of the ſame opinion,<note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>Relation of the ſtate of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig. cap.</hi> 47.</note> and calleth it <hi>the only remedie</hi> in ſuch times of controuerſies about religion. <hi>D. Sutcliffe</hi> hath theſe wordes:<note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>Sutcl. ſubu. pag.</hi> 119.</note> 
                  <hi>Generall Councels haue ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer aigne authority in externall gouernement.</hi> And againe:<note n="e" place="margin">
                     <hi>Sutc. againſt D. Kelliſon, p.</hi> 41. 42. 102.</note> 
                  <hi>Falſe it is, that we will admit no judge but Scriptures, for we appeale ſtill to a lawfull generall Councell.</hi>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">Sutcl. ſubu. epiſt. dedicat.</note> 
                  <hi>We hold all the Chriſtian faith explaned in the ſix ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Councels.</hi> D. <hi>Field</hi> is ſo cleare in this queſtion, that he telleth vs: firſt,<note n="g" place="margin">
                     <hi>Field pag.</hi> 226. <hi>cap.</hi> 16.</note> 
                  <hi>Priuate interpretations doe not binde vs, nor are propoſed to that purpoſe:</hi> ſecondly he teacheth,<note n="h" place="margin">
                     <hi>Field p.</hi> 228</note> that only <hi>Biſhops aſſembled in a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Councell haue authority, to interpret Scriptures, and by their authority, to ſuppreſſe all them that gaine-ſay ſuch interpretation, and ſubject euery man that ſhall diſobey ſuch determinations, as they conſent vpon, to excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication and cenſures of like nature:</hi> Hitherto of the higheſt dignity of generall Councels. Nowe let vs examine by theſe <hi>Protestants,</hi> whether they be for them, or <hi>Catholikes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That they be not, nor can be for <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> thus I demonſtrate from themſelues. The wordes of the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Relator of religion are theſe:<note n="i" place="margin">
                     <hi>Relation of religion, c.</hi> 47</note> 
                  <hi>The</hi> Proteſtants <hi>are ſeuered bandes, or rather ſcattered troopes, each drawing a diuers way, without any meanes to pacifie their quarrels, to take vp their controuerſies. No Prince with any preeminence of juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, aboue the reſt: no Patriarke, one or more, to haue a common ſuperin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance or care of their Churches, for correspondency and vnity: no ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry way to aſſemble a generall Councell of their part, the only hope remayning euer to aſſwage their contentions:</hi> Hitherto the Relator. Where vve ſee, that firſt the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> are diuided; ſecondly, they are without any meanes of vnion in controuerſies; there is no juriſdiction a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them; no way for that, which is the only hope to end conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in religion: therefore, this only and higheſt remedie by gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Councels, cannot poſſibly be for them; except they will haue an Vnion, Church, Faith, Truth, and Religion vnpoſſible. The ſame is ſufficiently alſo proued before, from <hi>D. Couell</hi> in my Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter<note n="k" place="margin">
                     <hi>Cap.</hi> 3. <hi>ſupr. &amp; Couell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the plea of the Innoc. pag.</hi> 103. 104 105. 106 107 108. 109.</note> of the Popes authority; where he alloweth of neceſſity, one
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:15902:15"/> higheſt, chiefe, ſpirituall commander in the Church, to ſuch pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes. And ſhewing how before the time of <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> there could be no pretence of any Councell to be aſſembled, but by the ſpiritual authority; he addeth thus:<note n="l" place="margin">
                     <hi>Couell ſupr. pag.</hi> 110.</note> 
                  <hi>The Synode of</hi> Rome <hi>(in the yeare</hi> 225) <hi>called by</hi> Cornelius (Pope of <hi>Rome) againſt</hi> Nouatus, <hi>conſiſted of three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore Biſhops. &amp; many others of the Clergie.</hi> And further in theſe wordes:<note n="m" place="margin">
                     <hi>page</hi> 109.</note> 
                  <hi>And after, when Princes came to embrace the faith, the beſt meanes they could deuiſe, to procure peace and aduance religion, was by their lawes to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre</hi> Eccleſiaſticall <hi>cauſes, to</hi> Eccleſiaſticall <hi>judges.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nowe concerning the <hi>Roman</hi> Church: firſt, the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Relator of religion, which hath excluded <hi>Proteſtants</hi> from al hope of any ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Councell, writeth of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church in the ſame place, and in theſe wordes:<note n="n" place="margin">
                     <hi>Relation of relig. ſupr. cap.</hi> 47.</note> 
                  <hi>The other</hi> (Catholikes) <hi>haue the Pope as a common father, aduiſer, and conductor to them al, to reconcile their jarres, to appeaſe their diſpleaſures, to decide their difference, aboue all thinges to drawe their religion by conſent of Councels, to vnity.</hi> And this is ſo cleare, in the judgement of al theſe <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> that when they denie the authority of generall Councels, they haue no pretence of excuſe, but becauſe they were called by the Popes authority; ſo <hi>D. Field</hi>
                  <note n="o" place="margin">Field booke of the church</note>, <hi>D. Sut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cliffe</hi>
                  <note n="p" place="margin">Sutcl. ſubu. againſt Kel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſon, &amp;c.</note>, <hi>M. Willet</hi>
                  <note n="q" place="margin">Will. Antil.</note>, and the reſt. And yet <hi>D. Fields</hi> argument or rule of the <hi>Paſtour of an Apoſtolike Church, the primatiue Church, and holy Fathers conſenting,</hi> doth warrant vs, that priuiledge euer belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to the See of Rome, that without the conſent thereof, no Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell could be called, none confirmed; as Pope <hi>Damaſus</hi>
                  <note n="r" place="margin">
                     <hi>Damaſ. epiſt. ad Illiric. hiſt. tripart. lib.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 28. <hi>vel</hi> 29. <hi>Theodor. hiſt. Socrat. hiſt. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 17. <hi>Sozo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
                  </note>, the ancient Fathers, and Hyſtorians witneſſe. And the Biſhoppe of <hi>Wincheſter</hi> graunteth theſe propoſitions:<note n="ſ" place="margin">
                     <hi>True diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce p.</hi> 66. 67 <hi>edit. an.</hi> 1586</note> 
                  <hi>The Canon of the primatiue Church made euery thing voide, that was done without the Biſhop of</hi> Rome. And againe: <hi>The Canon of the primatiue Church forbad any Councell to be called without his conſent.</hi>
                  <note n="t" place="margin">
                     <hi>Middleton papiſtom. pag.</hi> 39.</note> 
                  <hi>M. Middleton</hi> telleth vs that the firſt <hi>Nicen</hi> Councell did approue <hi>the dignity of Rome</hi> (at the leaſt) <hi>ouer the</hi> Weſt <hi>prouinces by old cuſtome.</hi> And if vve ſhould enter into particulers: Firſt, <hi>B. Bilſon</hi> will tell vs, that the Councell of <hi>Conſtance</hi>
                  <note n="u" place="margin">
                     <hi>p.</hi> 119 120.</note>, vvhere the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> doctrine was condemned in <hi>Huſſe</hi> and <hi>Wicliffe;</hi> was a generall Councell. So he witneſſeth of the Councell of <hi>Baſil</hi>
                  <note n="x" place="margin">
                     <hi>p.</hi> 124. 125.</note>, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning the ſame for hereſie. <hi>M. Willet</hi>
                  <note n="y" place="margin">
                     <hi>Willet Synopſ. controuerſ.</hi> 1. <hi>q.</hi> 7. <hi>Limbomastix apud Parkes, p.</hi> 137. 180.</note> both in his <hi>Synopſis</hi> and <hi>Lymbomaſtix)</hi> as <hi>M. Parkes</hi> is witneſſe againſt him: and himſelfe alſo ſo accounteth it) graunteth the ſame of the Councell of <hi>Florence,</hi>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:15902:15"/> where the ſeauen Sacraments, Purgatory, the Popes Supremacy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> were confirmed. Of the Councell of <hi>Trent</hi> no man will queſtion: And yet <hi>D. Doue</hi> hath aſſured vs before,<note n="z" place="margin">
                     <hi>Doue perſw. pag.</hi> 14.</note> that there were preſent in that Councell, <hi>ſix Cardinals, foure Legates, three Patriarkes, two and thirty Archbiſhops, two hundred twenty eight Biſhops.</hi> The third part of ſuch an aſſembly, would haue beene a great countenance to <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant</hi> religion, farre greater then euer it had, or is like to procure. <hi>D. Couell</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Couell def. of Hook. p.</hi> 21</note> and <hi>M. Parkes</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Parkes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt limbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſtix p.</hi> 176</note> cite &amp; approue as a rule of faith, the great Councell of <hi>Lateran,</hi> where <hi>tranſubſtantiation</hi> was defined: and joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth it with the primatiue Councels of <hi>Epheſus</hi> and <hi>Chalcedon,</hi> and in the high matter of faith, the <hi>Deity of the holy Ghoſt.</hi> And to aſcend to the firſt of <hi>Nice,</hi> the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> haue confeſſed before,<note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>cap.</hi> 4. <hi>ſupr.</hi>
                  </note> that Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures which we receiue, and they denie, were there approued. <hi>M. Willet</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>Will. Antil. pag.</hi> 88. 89.</note> calleth the primatiue Councels of <hi>Neocaeſarea, Toletane,</hi> the firſt and the fixt generall Councell, allowed before by <hi>D. Sutcliffe</hi> (wherein both generall and prouinciall precedent Councels, vvere approued) <hi>The Papall Church, Popery, doctrine in Popery.</hi> And of the ſeauenth generall Councell, he writeth thus:<note n="e" place="margin">
                     <hi>Will. Antil<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> pag.</hi> 178.</note> 
                  <hi>The</hi> Greekes <hi>in a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Councell held at</hi> Nice, <hi>confirmed and allowed the adoration of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages.</hi> But this may ſuffice of this queſtion, for both the Popes ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preamacy from the beginning, and the authority of all ancient Councels, Fathers, and Hyſtories, are ſo manifeſt for the preſent doctrine of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church; That <hi>M. Middleton</hi> telleth vs:<note n="f" place="margin">
                     <hi>Middleton papiſtomast. pag.</hi> 200.</note> 
                  <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pias</hi> (liuing in the Apoſtles time) <hi>taught</hi> Peters <hi>primacy or</hi> Romiſh <hi>Epiſcopality.</hi> Concerning the ſecond he vvriteth in theſe vvordes:<note n="g" place="margin">
                     <hi>page</hi> 193. <hi>ſupr.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Peruſing Councels, Fathers, and Stories from the Apoſtles forward, we finde the print of the Popes feete.</hi> Whereby is manifeſt, that euen from the Apoſtles to this preſent, the doctrine of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> was alwaies (as occaſion vvas giuen) approued, decreed, and taught by the holy Councels, Fathers, and Hyſtories of all ages.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Chapter 9.</hi> The teſtimonie of ancient Fathers of great authority, and for the doctrine of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church.</head>
               <p>LASTLY, in theſe generall queſtions, or directions in religion, let vs come to the teſtimony of the holy and learned Fathers,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:15902:16"/> of the primatiue Church (although of theſe it appeareth by the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Chapter;) And conſider firſt, the value and dignity of their authority: ſecondly, to whoſe cauſe, whether of <hi>Catholikes</hi> or <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants</hi> it beareth witneſſe.</p>
               <p>The Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter</hi> in his <hi>Suruey of Chriſtes ſufferings,</hi> wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth thus:<note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>B. Bilſons Suruey p.</hi> 85.</note> 
                  <hi>The ancient conſent of Godly Fathers, is with great care to be ſearched, and followed of vs, chiefly in the rule of faith.</hi> And againe:<note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>pa.</hi> 82. <hi>ſup.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>We reſt vpon the Scriptures of God, vpon the authority of the ancient Doctors, and Councels.</hi> And to the objection of thoſe <hi>Proteſtants</hi> which ſay:<note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>page</hi> 83.</note> 
                  <hi>The Canon of the Scriptures is perfect, and ſufficient in it ſelfe for all thinges; therefore, what neede is there that the authority of</hi> Eccleſiaſticall <hi>interpretation, ſhould be joyned with it?</hi> He anſwereth with <hi>Vincentius Lirinenſis,</hi> in theſe wordes: <hi>Leaſt euery man ſhould wreſt the Scriptures to his fanſie, and ſucke thence not the truth, but the patronage of his errour;</hi> And he addeth, that <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> gaue this reſpect, not only to <hi>gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall</hi> Councels, but to the <hi>teſtimonies of particuler Fathers,</hi> Ireneus, Cyprian, <hi>Hilarius,</hi> Ambroſe, <hi>Gregory,</hi> Chriſoſtome, <hi>Baſil,</hi> and others.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>D. Sutcliffe</hi> writeth thus:<note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>Sutcl. ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſ. pag.</hi> 87.</note> 
                  <hi>We acknowledge the faith of the Fathers, of the fourth, fift, and ſixt ages, and adjoyne our ſelues to that Church.</hi> And againſt <hi>D. Kelliſon</hi> he vſeth theſe wordes:<note n="e" place="margin">
                     <hi>Sutcliffe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt D. Kel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liſon, pag.</hi> 17.</note> 
                  <hi>The Fathers in all points of faith are for vs</hi> (Proteſtants) <hi>and not for the Pope.</hi> M. <hi>Willet</hi> in the end of his <hi>Antilogie,</hi> ſweareth the matter in this manner:<note n="f" place="margin">
                     <hi>Willet An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilog. p.</hi> 263.</note> 
                  <hi>I take God to witneſſe, before whome I muſt render account,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>That the ſame faith and religion, which I defend, is taught, and confirmed in the more ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiall points, by theſe Hyſtorians, Councels, Fathers, that liued within fiue, or ſix hundred yeares after Chriſt.</hi> And in the page following, his wordes be theſe:<note n="g" place="margin">
                     <hi>p.</hi> 264. <hi>ſupr</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>It is moſt notoriouſly euident, that for the groſſeſt points of Popery, as tranſubſtantiation, ſacrifice of Maſſe, worſhipping of Images, juſtification by workes, the ſupreamacy of the Pope, prohibition of Mariage, and ſuch other, they</hi> (Catholikes) <hi>haue no ſhewe at al of any euidence from the Fathers, within fiue hundred yeares of Chriſt.</hi> And thus againe:<note n="h" place="margin">
                     <hi>Willet An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilog. pa.</hi> 271.</note> 
                  <hi>The ancient Fathers that liued within ſix hundred yeares after Chriſt, are againſt them.</hi> And thus I might alleadge from others, eſpecially triumphing in this manner, either when they write againſt <hi>Puritans,</hi> (whome the Fathers condemne) as the Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter</hi> is cited: or when they ſpeake in generall, and the authorities of Fathers are neither to be anſwered, as produced by <hi>Catholikes,</hi> or alleadged for
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:15902:16"/> 
                  <hi>Proteſtants;</hi> as it appeareth in thoſe places of <hi>D. Sutcliffe,</hi> and <hi>M. Willets</hi> great and glorious ſpeaches of the Fathers. But when theſe men are either to anſwere thoſe primatiue Fathers, cited for our cauſe; or ſtand vpon their teſtimony in particuler for themſelues, <hi>the caſe is altered,</hi> as is objected<note n="i" place="margin">
                     <hi>Apud B. Bilſ. Suruey, p.</hi> 84<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> to the Biſhop of <hi>Winchester,</hi> by his <hi>Puritan</hi> oppoſite. But howe truly they keepe their vvordes and oathes, in theſe proteſtations, ſhall be hereafter declared: for the preſent; it is expected by all <hi>Proteſtants</hi> that deale ſincerely, that their religion ſhould be agreeable, to the doctrine of the ancient, and primatiue Fathers: Therefore, his Majeſty eſteeming them with due regard, hath pleaſed to ſentence theſe in Parliament:<note n="k" place="margin">
                     <hi>K. ſpeach Parlia.</hi> 1603</note> 
                  <hi>I will euer yeeld all reuerence to Antiquity.</hi> And in the publike confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, in theſe wordes:<note n="l" place="margin">
                     <hi>Conference, pag.</hi> 73.</note> 
                  <hi>For my part, I knowe not howe to anſwere the objection of Papiſts, when they charge vs with nouelties, but to tell them, that their abuſes are newe.</hi> And approueth, the dayes and time of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> in the primatiue Church, a rule of religion; ſaying:<note n="m" place="margin">
                     <hi>Conference ſupr. pag.</hi> 69.</note> Conſtantine <hi>is not to be appeached of ſuperſtition, but thinges then vſed may ſtill be continued.</hi> Alſo in his firſt ſpeach in Parliament, he would haue <hi>all nouelties renounced.</hi> And of the ſame minde (no doubt) be all ſincerely meaning <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> which truſt vnto, and are directed by the ſermons, citations, and bookes of theſe Doctors, &amp; teachers among them. But it will nowe appeare, that they are ſo farre from juſtifying their former oathes, proteſtations, and aſſertions, that they acknowledge thoſe primatiue Fathers, to be for <hi>Catholikes;</hi> and both vvrite, and cenſure thoſe moſt holy and learned men for that cauſe, with vnciuill, contemptuous, barbarous, and irreligious ſpeaches. Firſt, <hi>M. Wotton</hi> expreſly controleth the recited ſentence of his Majeſty, concerning the time of <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> and antiquity: for a <hi>Catholike</hi> Authour citing<note n="n" place="margin">The Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Authour againſt Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins in prefat</note>, and humbly accepting it for a rule of triall; <hi>M. Wotton</hi> writeth thus:<note n="o" place="margin">
                     <hi>Wot. def. of Per. p.</hi> 15. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>The triall of doctrine, is not to be featched from the opinions and examples of men.</hi> And againe:<note n="p" place="margin">
                     <hi>page</hi> 16.</note> 
                  <hi>It may not ſeeme ſtrange, if ſuperſtition were crept into the Church, before</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantines <hi>time.</hi> Let vs proceede. <hi>D. Couell</hi> (a man not of the raſheſt judgement) hath honoured <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> before, vvith the greateſt commendation of learning; yet, <hi>M. Wotton</hi> writeth:<note n="q" place="margin">
                     <hi>W. ſup. p.</hi> 8.</note> 
                  <hi>We neede not feare</hi> S. Auguſtine <hi>though againſt vs.</hi>
                  <note n="r" place="margin">
                     <hi>page</hi> 17.</note> Euſebius <hi>is to be reprehended.</hi>
                  <note n="ſ" place="margin">
                     <hi>page</hi> 9.</note> 
                  <hi>There was want of modeſty and truth alſo in the treatiſe of</hi> Hierome <hi>againſt</hi> Vigilantius.<note n="t" place="margin">
                     <hi>page</hi> 88.</note> 
                  <hi>The ancient Fathers ſpake more like Philoſophers,</hi>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:15902:17"/> 
                  <hi>then Diuines.</hi>
                  <note n="u" place="margin">
                     <hi>page</hi> 118.</note> 
                  <hi>It is more then I knowe, that</hi> Gregory <hi>is a Saint.</hi>
                  <note n="x" place="margin">
                     <hi>page</hi> 224.</note> 
                  <hi>The Authour of the Epiſtle to the</hi> Philippians, <hi>attributed to</hi> S. Ignatius, <hi>is an vnfit judge in controuerſies of diuinity.</hi>
                  <note n="y" place="margin">
                     <hi>page</hi> 422.</note> Tertullians <hi>witneſſe is of ſmall authority.</hi>
                  <note n="z" place="margin">
                     <hi>page</hi> 440.</note> Damaſcene <hi>is not greatly to be respected.</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>page</hi> 462.</note> Origen <hi>is ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally condemned.</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>page</hi> 340.</note> Ignatius <hi>Epiſtle to the</hi> Romans (approued by <hi>S. Hierome,</hi> and <hi>Proteſtants) is a counterfeit</hi> Ignatius, <hi>for teaching merit of good workes.</hi>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>page</hi> 387.</note> Cyprian <hi>is too farre carryed away, ſince he aſcribeth to almeſdeedes, the purging of ſinne.</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>page</hi> 467.</note> Ireneus <hi>judgement is little to be respected.</hi>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">
                     <hi>page</hi> 494.</note> Tertullians <hi>teſtimony is not worth anſwering.</hi> Tertullian <hi>and</hi> Origen <hi>may be joyned together.</hi>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">
                     <hi>page</hi> 495.</note> Chryſoſtomes <hi>Rhethoricke is better then his Logicke.</hi>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">
                     <hi>page</hi> 495.</note> Hieromes <hi>authority in the caſe of ſingle life, is not much worth.</hi>
                  <note n="h" place="margin">
                     <hi>page</hi> 500.</note> 
                  <hi>Thoſe Chriſtian Fathers which condemned</hi> Iouinian (as <hi>S. Auguſtine,</hi> Ambroſe, <hi>Hierome,</hi> &amp;c.) <hi>delt vnchriſtianly with him.</hi>
                  <note n="i" place="margin">
                     <hi>p.</hi> 519. 520.</note> 
                  <hi>The authority of the ancient writers</hi> (Athanaſius, <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> Hierome) <hi>concluding a worke of perfection from thoſe wordes of Chriſt,</hi> goe and ſell all, &amp;c. <hi>is not to be admitted.</hi>
                  <note n="k" place="margin">
                     <hi>page</hi> 543.</note> 
                  <hi>The authority of</hi> Clement <hi>of</hi> Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dria, <hi>and</hi> Auguſtine, <hi>with the ſchoole Doctors, is inferior to the</hi> Iewes.<note n="l" place="margin">
                     <hi>p.</hi> 545<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 546.</note> Origen <hi>and</hi> Theodoret (vvhome before he preferreth<note n="m" place="margin">
                     <hi>page</hi> 484.</note> aboue S. Auguſtine) <hi>ouerthrowe their owne diſtinction.</hi>
                  <note n="n" place="margin">
                     <hi>page</hi> 594.</note> Lactantius <hi>though he were an ancient Chriſtian, yet in his verſes</hi> (of vvorſhipping the Croſſe) <hi>he ſheweth himſelfe liker a light Poët, then a graue writer.</hi> And no meruaile, though this <hi>Proteſtant</hi> be ſo angry with the ancient Fathers, for teaching and maintayning that doctrine, vvhich the <hi>Roman</hi> Church nowe holdeth, as appeareth before. For he exclay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth moſt barbarouſly and vvithout reſpect, euen againſt all the Kings of this, and other nations, for the ſame cauſe; his wordes be theſe:<note n="o" place="margin">
                     <hi>page</hi> 53.</note> 
                  <hi>The Kings of</hi> England <hi>and</hi> Scotland, <hi>&amp;c. were Sathans ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, when they were of the Popes religion:</hi> Hitherto <hi>M. Wotten;</hi> next let vs come to <hi>M. Perkins,</hi> whome he defendeth. <hi>M. Perkins</hi> writeth thus:<note n="p" place="margin">
                     <hi>Perkin. pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blem. pag.</hi> 4.</note> 
                  <hi>The Fathers haue ſpoken many thinges incommodiouſly of holy thinges.</hi>
                  <note n="q" place="margin">
                     <hi>pag.</hi> 93. 94.</note> 
                  <hi>The ancient Fathers did ſinne in the inuocation of Saints: yea, were guilty of ſacrilege, ſuch were</hi> Paulinus, <hi>Fortunatus,</hi> S. Leo, <hi>S. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phrem,</hi> S. Flugentius, <hi>Petrus Domianus,</hi> Proſper.<note n="r" place="margin">
                     <hi>page</hi> 105.</note> 
                  <hi>The ancient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſometimes ſpeake inconueniently, of the article of juſtification:</hi>
                  <note n="ſ" place="margin">
                     <hi>page</hi> 184.</note> 
                  <hi>Some of the ancient Fathers (as</hi> Tertullian <hi>and</hi> Cyprian) <hi>are</hi> Montaniſts; <hi>or (at the leaſt) doe erre filthily, for making Confirmation a Sacrament.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>D. Sutcliffe,</hi> vvho ſo much before reuerenced the Fathers in vvordes, nowe writeth in this manner.<note n="t" place="margin">
                     <hi>Sutcl. ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſ. pag.</hi> 5.</note> Metaphraſtes <hi>is a lying</hi>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:15902:17"/> 
                  <hi>pedant, writing more lyes, then leaues.</hi>
                  <note n="u" place="margin">
                     <hi>page</hi> 8. 9.</note> Bede <hi>reporteth too many thinges by heare-ſay.</hi> Ado <hi>is a fabulous writer.</hi>
                  <note n="x" place="margin">
                     <hi>page</hi> 9.</note> 
                  <hi>The hiſtory of King</hi> Lucius <hi>his conuerſion</hi> (teſtified by ſo many hyſtories) <hi>may well be paragoned, with the tales of King</hi> Arthure, <hi>Sir</hi> Triſtram, <hi>and</hi> Lancelot Dulacke.<note n="y" place="margin">
                     <hi>page</hi> 19.</note> 
                  <hi>The</hi> Brittaines <hi>haue cauſe to detest the memory of</hi> Auguſtine.</p>
               <p>Let vs next come to <hi>M. Willet,</hi> the great profeſſor of Diuinity, who hath taken ſo ſolemne an oath before, that the Fathers be for his cauſe. To ſhewe his juſt dealings, I will only vſe the teſtimony of a <hi>Proteſtant</hi> againſt him. <hi>M. Parkes</hi> vvriteth of him in theſe wordes:<note n="z" place="margin">
                     <hi>Parkes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Limbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſtix, p.</hi> 170</note> 
                  <hi>He condemneth all the ancient Fathers for dreamers.</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>page</hi> 151.</note> 
                  <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demneth all the Fathers.</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">Defen. of the third teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny. ſect. kkk.</note> 
                  <hi>He condemneth all learned and Godly Diuines for enemies of Chriſtes Croſſe, and blaſphemers of his paſsion. He juſtifieth most wicked</hi> Heretikes, <hi>and condemneth moſt holy Fathers.</hi>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>Defen. of the firſt &amp; ſecond testimony. p.</hi> 2 5. <hi>ſect.</hi> 18. 21. <hi>pag.</hi> 181. 166 101. 100. <hi>defenc. of the</hi> 2. <hi>place. ſect.</hi> 10. 11. 20. <hi>defenc. of the</hi> 3. <hi>testimony, ſect.</hi> 7. 12. 15. 16. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>He falſly tranſlateth, corrupteth, indignely handleth, clippeth, ſhamefully corrupteth, injuriouſly handleth, greatly abuſeth, vntruly alleageth, miſquoteth, may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, miſtranſlateth, much abuſeth, notably corrupteth, &amp;c.</hi> S. Auguſtine, <hi>Origen,</hi> S. Ambroſe, <hi>S. Chryſoſtome,</hi> S. Leo, <hi>S. Hierome.</hi> Tertullian, <hi>S. Bernard,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>fathereth falſe-boodes vpon them, peruerteth their true arguments, corrupteth their wordes.</hi> And further in particuler, for thoſe bookes which he hath written againſt <hi>Catholikes,</hi> as his <hi>Synopſis</hi> and <hi>Antilogie,</hi> he reproueth<note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>Parkes ſup. pag.</hi> 7. 10. 19. 20. 21. 22. 23. 24. 25. <hi>&amp; def. of the</hi> 3. <hi>test. ſect.</hi> 16. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> and diſalloweth, telling vs that in them he <hi>deceiueth the world, belyeth</hi> Bellarmine, <hi>and</hi> Catholike <hi>writers.</hi> And he is as bold with his Majeſty, calling his ſentence (<note n="e" place="margin">
                     <hi>Parkes ſup. pag.</hi> 28.</note> 
                  <hi>that the</hi> Roman <hi>Church is our mother Church) a fooliſh conceite and imagination.</hi> And no meruaile vvhen he is as familiar vvith the holy Scriptures them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, as this <hi>Proteſtant</hi> writeth thus:<note n="f" place="margin">
                     <hi>Parkes ſup. defence of the</hi> 1. 2. 3. <hi>test.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>He ſtrangely peruerteth, belyeth, depraueth, abuſeth, much abuſeth, falſifyeth holy Scriptures.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>M. Ormerod</hi> hath vvritten a booke expreſly againſt the <hi>Puritans,</hi> intituling the ſame <hi>the picture of a Puritan,</hi> condemning them of <hi>Idolatry, Hereſies, Schiſme:</hi> And yet to ſhewe vvhat credit there is in theſe men, and vvhat truſt to their doctrine, himſelfe is ſo farre a <hi>Puritan</hi> in judgement, and in the maine article, vvhich coſt the Biſhoppe of <hi>Winchester</hi> ſuch paines, that he is not only at defiance with all Fathers:<note n="g" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ormero. pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganopapiſt. pag.</hi> 44.</note> but compareth the <hi>Article and beleefe of Christes deſcending into hell,</hi> to the fable of <hi>Hercules,</hi> fayned to goe thither, and featch from thence <hi>Theſeus,</hi> Pyrithous, and <hi>Cerberus</hi> the great Dogge of hell, with three heades.</p>
               <p>Next let vs come to <hi>M. Middleton;</hi> in this manner he vvriteth:
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:15902:18"/>
                  <note n="h" place="margin">
                     <hi>Middleton Papiſtomast. pag.</hi> 40.</note> 
                  <hi>The credit of men is but a ſandy foundation to build vpon.</hi> And hauing told <hi>S. Epiphanius</hi>
                  <note n="i" place="margin">
                     <hi>page</hi> 27.</note> 
                  <hi>that he loſt the booke of the Apoſtles conſtitutions out of his boſome,</hi> which he cited <hi>haereſ.</hi> 45. He addeth:<note n="k" place="margin">
                     <hi>page</hi> 45.</note> 
                  <hi>I muſt craue leaue to ſay of</hi> Epiphanius; <hi>many aſſertions he counted for hereſies, which were not hereſies: many aſſertions he counted not hereſies, which are hereſies.</hi> And al this, becauſe he condemneth diuers <hi>Proteſtant</hi> points of here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, and juſtifieth the contrary for <hi>Catholike</hi> doctrine. Againe thus of <hi>Dioniſius</hi> the <hi>Arëopagite:</hi>
                  <note n="l" place="margin">
                     <hi>page</hi> 49.</note> Denis <hi>his anſwere is ſhort-heeld, ready to fall backe;</hi> becauſe he teacheth prayer for the dead. And where <hi>S. Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe</hi> teacheth the doctrine of <hi>tranſubſtantiation,</hi> M. <hi>Middleton</hi> tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth vs,<note n="m" place="margin">
                     <hi>page</hi> 61.</note> 
                  <hi>He is guilty of preſumptuous and desporate blaſphemy.</hi> He ſcoffeth<note n="n" place="margin">
                     <hi>page</hi> 64.</note> at <hi>S. Chryſoſtome,</hi> and teacheth him howe to ſpeake, for teaching the doctrine of prayer for the dead. And againe, he vſeth this mocke againſt him, for calling it an Apoſtolicall Tradition:<note n="o" place="margin">
                     <hi>page</hi> 66.</note> 
                  <hi>Well might</hi> Chryſoſtome <hi>ſay, the Apoſtles knewe what profite redoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the dead, by prayer for them; for himſelfe knewe not.</hi> And thus in generall:<note n="p" place="margin">
                     <hi>page</hi> 133.</note> 
                  <hi>The Fathers ſometime went beyond the bondes of ſobriety, in the doctrine of chaſtity.</hi>
                  <note n="q" place="margin">
                     <hi>page</hi> 134.</note> 
                  <hi>The Fathers are not fit judges to determine either of Prieſts marriage, or vowes of chaſtity.</hi> And for this doctrine thus he writeth of <hi>S. Ambroſe:</hi>
                  <note n="r" place="margin">
                     <hi>page</hi> 135.</note> 
                  <hi>That man hath the Apoſtaticall Dragon, the Diuell dwelling in him.</hi> And ſo, he will <hi>ſend</hi> Ambroſe <hi>away with his Quietus est.</hi>
                  <note n="ſ" place="margin">
                     <hi>page</hi> 137</note> Chryſoſtome <hi>is ſo hotte in his amplifications, that he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gets himſelfe.</hi>
                  <note n="t" place="margin">
                     <hi>page</hi> 138.</note> Chryſoſtome <hi>in his vehemency, goeth beyond meaſure in reprehending; and the Chriſtians of his time in their lightneſſe, went beyond meaſure in vowing.</hi>
                  <note n="u" place="margin">
                     <hi>page</hi> 141.</note> 
                  <hi>The Canons which</hi> Epiphanius <hi>citeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Prieſts marriage, are Apocryphall.</hi>
                  <note n="x" place="margin">
                     <hi>page</hi> 143.</note> He was <hi>to partiall affected in this matter.</hi>
                  <note n="y" place="margin">
                     <hi>page</hi> 144.</note> 
                  <hi>The ancient Fathers did erre, and we diſſent from them in ſome points of doctrine.</hi>
                  <note n="z" place="margin">
                     <hi>page</hi> 156.</note> Auguſtine <hi>was a moſt ſubtile diſputer: yet, a quicke wit ſooneſt falleth into contradiction.</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>page</hi> 161.</note> 
                  <hi>Neither is</hi> Hilary <hi>(howe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer the</hi> Romiſh <hi>Church hath made him a Saint) ouer haſtily to be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued.</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>p.</hi> 179. 180.</note> 
                  <hi>Ireneus,</hi> Hilary, <hi>and Epiphanius</hi> (for defending free will) <hi>are</hi> Pelagian <hi>Heretikes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is written againſt the Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter</hi> (who in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of this Chapter gaue ſuch reuerence to the Fathers) in theſe wordes by his <hi>Puritan</hi> oppoſite:<note n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>B. Bilſons Suruey p.</hi> 84.</note> 
                  <hi>Al this great ſhewe of cleauing to the Fathers judgement, is but coloured in you. For in other points againe we ſee, when they ſpeake not to your liking, the caſe is altered. You forſake the ancient and learned Fathers, you contemne and diſpiſe them.</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">
                     <hi>page</hi> 85.</note> 
                  <hi>You affirme</hi>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:15902:18"/> 
                  <hi>againſt all the Fathers.</hi> (<note n="e" place="margin">98.</note> 
                  <hi>You little regard the ſecond doctrine of the Fathers?</hi> Hitherto the <hi>Puritant</hi> againſt the <hi>Proteſtants;</hi> nowe let vs heare the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> againſt the <hi>Puritans.</hi> This <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Biſhoppe intituleth one Treatiſe thus:<note n="f" place="margin">
                     <hi>pa.</hi> 98. <hi>ſupr.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>The defendors diſdaine of the Fathers.</hi> Others<note n="g" place="margin">
                     <hi>p.</hi> 274. 275.</note> 
                  <hi>wreſted, and leudly falſifyed.</hi> And againe:<note n="h" place="margin">Prefa. to the King ſupr.</note> 
                  <hi>They condemns all the Fathers</hi> Greeke <hi>and</hi> Latin; <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> conſpiring againſt the truth and peruerting the Scriptures.</hi> This is too much of this diſtaſting matter: they vvhich would ſee more particulers, may finde them applyed in my particuler queſtions hereafter.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>The <hi>10.</hi> Chapter, or Concluſion of the generall queſtions or rules in religion.</head>
               <p>WHEREFORE, ſeing vve <hi>Catholikes</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> are only, or principally, vrged, moued, and ſollicited, by the preſent <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Doctors, Diuines, and Teachers of this Kingdome, to forſake that religion, and Church wherein we liue, a thing not to be deſired by them, or effected by vs without inſtruction of the truth, if we were in errour: (as the Biſhop of <hi>Durham</hi> ſufficiently preached<note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Serm. of the B. of Durbam</hi> 19. <hi>Mart.</hi> 1603. <hi>cit. K. ſpeach in parl.</hi>
                  </note> before his Majeſty, the firſt day of his firſt Parliament) we earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and humbly deſire, that thoſe miſeries, vvhich we haue ſo long hitherto ſuffered, as they be forgiuen by vs; ſo they may be ſufficient vnto them: which nowe doe teach, direct, and inſtruct vs, rather to continue our faith and religion, as the moſt certaine, ſecure, and ready way of ſaluation.</p>
               <p>For they haue inſtructed vs in their lateſt vvritings, that the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> is the true Church of Chriſt, where ſaluation is to be had; wherein ſo many Princes, Prelates, Doctors, and of all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, haue beene glorious Saints. The greateſt agents for the Pope, <hi>The crownes and fore-tops of all Popery,</hi> (as <hi>M. Middleton</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">
                     <hi>Middleton Papiſtomaſs. pag.</hi> 127.</note> plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth to name <hi>S. Thomas Aquinas)</hi> were moſt renowmed, their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine excellent, and ſecure.</p>
               <p>That the <hi>Catholikes</hi> opinion generally receiued, of the Popes ſpirituall preeminence, was euer claymed (euen from Scripture) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd practiſed by the Apoſtolike <hi>Roman</hi> See, ouer the whole Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian world, from the time of <hi>S. Peter,</hi> to theſe our dayes.</p>
               <p>That all bookes, vvhich that Church receiueth for Canonicall
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:15902:19"/> Scriptures, are moſt true, deliuered for ſuch by the Apoſtles, reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renced for ſuch in the Church; and <hi>Proteſtants</hi> objections againſt them be friuoulous and confuted. That the true, and beſt tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of theſe holy Scriptures, with the lawfull, ſupreame, and bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding expoſition of them, together vvith Apoſtolicall Traditions (equall in authority to thoſe holy writings) the generall Councels, and Ancient, Holy, Learned primatiue Fathers, giue abſolute te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony, that the preſent <hi>Roman</hi> Church, <hi>is that company of holy ones, that houſe-hold of faith, that ſpouſe of Chriſt, and Church of the liuing God, which is the piller and ground of truth:</hi> which is ſo <hi>diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly take ſearched for, whoſe communion we must embrace, followe her directions, and rest in her judgement.</hi> And thus much of the firſt part of <hi>Protestants</hi> proofes, for <hi>Catholike</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>A PARIS.</p>
            <p>Chez François Gueffier, demeurant deuan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> la College de Cambray.</p>
            <p>M. D. C. VII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:15902:19"/>
            <head>THE TABLE OF THE FIRST PART OF PROTESTANT PROOFES, FOR CATHO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like religion.</head>
            <head type="sub">The firſt part entreating of the generall groundes, and authorities for true religion.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHAP.</hi> 1. The firſt Chapter teacheth by <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> the neceſsity of ſeeking, finding, and following the true Church. <hi>Page</hi> 7.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 2. The <hi>Roman</hi> Church euer was, and nowe is this true Church. <hi>page</hi> 8.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 3. The Biſhoppe of <hi>Rome</hi> by <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> euer was, and is ſupreame head of the true Church. <hi>page</hi> 13.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 4. All thoſe bookes which the <hi>Roman</hi> Church receiueth for Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, and <hi>Proteſtants</hi> heretofore denyed for ſuch, are proued by them to be Canonicall Scriptures. <hi>page</hi> 17.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 5. The vulgar <hi>Latin</hi> tranſlation of Scriptures, vſed of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Church, is the beſt: the <hi>Engliſh Proteſtant</hi> tranſlations are erroneous. <hi>page</hi> 21.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 6. The trueſt, higheſt, &amp; authoriſed interpretation of Scriptures, is in the <hi>Roman</hi> Church; and not with <hi>Proteſtants. page</hi> 23.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 7. Traditions are of equall authority with the Scriptures, and proue <hi>Catholike</hi> religion. <hi>page</hi> 25.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 8. The authority of generall Councels aboue all <hi>Proteſtant</hi> rules, make for the <hi>Catholike</hi> Church. <hi>page</hi> 28.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 9. Likewiſe of the authority of Fathers. <hi>page</hi> 31.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap.</hi> 10. The concluſion of the firſt part. <hi>page</hi> 37.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="argument">
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:15902:20"/>
            <head>THE TABLE OR ARGVMENT OF THE ſecond part, of <hi>Proteſtant</hi> proofes, for <hi>Catholikes</hi> religion, and recuſancy.</head>
            <p>THE particuler articles of Predeſtination, Iuſtification, Inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent grace, Merit and reward of good deedes, of keeping the Commandements, Free will, diſtinction of Precepts and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſailes, of Veniall and Mortall ſinnes, of Indulgences, reuerence to holy Images, reuerence to holy Reliques, prayer to Saints and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, publike Seruice not in the vulgar tongues, Church Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, Chriſtes reall preſence in the bleſſed Sacrament, Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation, Sacrifice of the Maſſe, ſingle life of Prieſts, vowes of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtity, Purgatory, and prayer for the Dead, The number of ſeauen Sacraments, their grace <hi>ex opere operato,</hi> and an ind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lible Character in ſome Sacraments.</p>
            <p>All which <hi>Catholike</hi> articles are proued, by the teſtimonies of ſuch <hi>Engliſh Proteſtant</hi> Doctors, and Diuines, as haue written ſince the beginning of his Majeſties raigne in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:15902:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
